<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Protestant mask taken off from the Jesuited Englishman being an answer to a book entituled Great Britain's just complaint.</title>
            <author>Comber, Thomas, 1645-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22733</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12234018</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12234018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 913:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Protestant mask taken off from the Jesuited Englishman being an answer to a book entituled Great Britain's just complaint.</title>
                  <author>Comber, Thomas, 1645-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 67, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Wilde for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692/3.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Comber. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Montgomery, James, --  Sir, d. 1694. --  Great Britain's just complaint for her late measures, present sufferings, and the future miseries she is exposed to.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Proteſtant Mask Taken off from the <hi>Jeſuited Engliſhman;</hi> BEING, AN ANSWER To a Book, Entituled, <hi>[GREAT-BRITAIN's Juſt Complaint.]</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. 1692.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>EDMUND BOHUN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Wilde,</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock,</hi> at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, 1692/3.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56682:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56682:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Proteſtant Mask</hi> Taken off from the Jeſuited Engliſh-man. OR, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere are no ſort of Men who can ſo dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly put on all Shapes as the refined Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and none ſo apt to be impoſed upon at this time by theſe <hi>Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raders,</hi> as King <hi>James</hi>'s Proteſtant Friends. The laſt Revolution gave as great a Blow to Popery, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would do to the Reformed Religion: ſo that they who wiſh well to the Roman, and ill to the Engliſh Church, muſt rail at the paſt Revolution, and adviſe us to another; they muſt cover the late King's real Faults, and brand the preſent with feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Crimes; they muſt ſtrain their Wits to repreſent King <hi>James</hi> as one who never did any Evil, and King <hi>William</hi> as if he never did any Good. This, with a few Harangues of Loyalty, and ſome ſhew of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the Proteſtant Religion, the diſguiſed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hopes will ſuffice to make thoſe Church-of-<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>-men, who are not ſatisfied with the Preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, venture into Arms to reſtore King <hi>James,</hi> wherein ſhould they proſper, it can ſerve the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56682:3"/>of none but <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and if they be unfortunate, it muſt end in the Ruine of the deluded <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers.</hi> In pure Charity to them therefore, and tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to my Country, I will examine the late Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, ſtiled, <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s <hi>Just Complaint,</hi> &amp;c. and briefly ſhew the Sophiſtry and Weakneſs of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, the Falſhood of his pretented Hiſtory, and the Malice as well as Danger of his Deſign. To which purpoſe I muſt paſs by his Flowers of Rhetorick, his innumerable and needleſs Repetitions and Tautolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, (which make up one half of the Book) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply only to that which ſeems material.</p>
            <p>He ſtumbles on a Contradiction very ominouſly at his firſt Step,
<note place="margin">Page 1.</note> affirming that our laſt Revolution ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a Parallel in antient or modern Hiſtory; yet immediately grants, <q>there are Inſtances in every Country of Subjects who have been forced by Arms to defend their Religion and Liberties againſt ſuch violent Acts of their Princes, as viſibly endangered the Frame of the Government; and that many Princes have loſt their Crowns by their Cruelty, and being obſtinately deaf to their Subjects Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Complaints.</q> Which Inſtances are all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels to our Revolution, excepting only that moſt of them have been more bloody and violent upon leſs Occaſions; and in few places, where a free People were ſo long and highly provoked, did the Criminals come off ſo eaſily.</p>
            <p>The next Exploit of this bold Writer is to arraign the whole Nation,
<note place="margin">Page 2.</note> and the wiſeſt Men in it, for Fools and Mad-men, as being impoſed on by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Ambition, and refuſing all Offers of Accommodation, and Expedients for Redreſs: Whereas our greateſt Stateſmen did examine theſe Offers and Expedients; and in the midſt of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberations,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56682:3"/>the late King went away privately for <hi>France,</hi> and ſo broke off the Treaty. With equal Truth and Modeſty he affirms, that all the Reaſons of this Revolution are baffled, and the Actors in it aſhamed of the Grounds they went upon. Yet ſtill there remain, it ſeems, two famous Pamphlets, which have put him to all his ſhifts to anſwer: one is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Pretences of the French Invaſion Examined;</hi> the other, <hi>A Letter to a Friend concerning the French Invaſion.</hi> And not to take notice of his blind Gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at, and rude Cenſures of the Authors, and the Papers themſelves, we will try how well he hath confuted them.</p>
            <p>After all the Reproaches of Folly and Fallacy caſt upon the firſt Author,
<note place="margin">Page 3.</note> he grants the Points he hath treated upon, are very weighty; and our profound Politician humbly follows the Steps of his contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Adverſary. And to prepare Men to revolt from this Government, and join with a <hi>French Invaſion,</hi> he undertakes to ſhew they ought to venture their Necks for another Revolution.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To repair the Injury done to King <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. To ſettle the Government upon its old <hi>Baſts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. To deliver our ſelves from the preſent Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings we lie under.</item>
               <item>4. To ſecure the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. To make out the Injury done to King <hi>James,</hi> he takes leave of the Papers he was anſwering, and runs back near 20 Years to make up a moſt ridiculous and improbable <hi>Invective</hi> againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> hoping to hide the juſt, real and honourable Cauſes of his Deſcent, (which were his Love to us, and to our Religion and Laws, then in extreme Danger by K. <hi>James</hi>'s Adminiſtration) by a falſe and groundleſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56682:4"/>Charge of his ambitious aiming at our Crown, before he could well write Man, and by accuſing him of all the Troubles of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d's Reign, which he aggravates by that Uncle's Tenderneſs for him. Which laſt Inſinuation ſhews the Truth of the reſt: for Sir <hi>W. Temple</hi> (who beſt knew) obſerves that K. <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d was ſo deep in the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> that he ſhamefully neglected his brave Nephew, when his Life, and the Safety of Chriſtendom lay at ſtake.</p>
            <p>But why doth this nameleſs Libeller dig ſo deep for hidden Cauſes of the Troubles of that Reign?
<note place="margin">Page 4.</note> The Growth of Arbitrary Power and Popery, the Duke's declaring himſelf Papiſt, the Breach of the Triple League, the Dutch War, the Intrigues with <hi>France,</hi> and the Popiſh Plot, were open and known Cauſes of theſe Troubles: And a few of them were ſufficient to make a People, ſo tender of their Liberties and Religion as the Engliſh are, to be uneaſy. Beſides, how came it to paſs that K. <hi>Charles,</hi> who was ſo very ſagacious, never diſcovered this, but to the great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction (not of his People, but) of his own Mind, as he declared in Parliament, married this Prince to his Niece, who was then generally ſuppoſed likely to ſucceed to the Engliſh Crown? And to ſhew this Match was no Force upon that King, the Noble Peer who adviſed the Match, was moſt dear to his then Maſter, and had a better Poſt in his Reign than that he now enjoys. The Duke perhaps might be averſe to this Match, as being likely to ſpoil his Deſigns of converting us, which would be difficult in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a Proteſtant Heir. The Bill of Excluſion, and the refuſing K. <hi>Charles</hi>'s Conceſſions, are next impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the P. of <hi>O.</hi> and his Friends, but very falſly; for the Popiſh Plot gave the pretence to that Bill, and the Zealots for it inclined to ſet up <hi>Monmouth</hi> or a Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56682:4"/>
As to the Conceſſions of a Fence againſt a Popiſh Succeſſor, if the P. of <hi>O.</hi> really had any Friends in that <hi>Parliament,</hi> and any ſuch Proſpect as is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there would not have been a fairer Opportunity to put him then into the greateſt Truſt and Power; but the Truth is, the Duke's Creatures in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> who knew he had rather not Reign, than be ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered and unabled to reſtore <hi>Popery,</hi> join'd with the <hi>Republicans</hi> to throw out thoſe Offers.</p>
            <p>As the Pagans of old were wont to put all the Curſes due to a City upon ſome hated Perſon,
<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> and then make him a Sufferer for them all; ſo this ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Railer</hi> uſes this moſt <hi>Heroick Prince,</hi> loading him with all the ill Things that were done here, in hopes to expoſe him to the Peoples Rage; Even the <hi>Quo-Warranto's</hi> deſigned to uſher in <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and cruſh his Friends, (if he had any) and <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Invaſion, the Succeſs of which had caſt out his Title, are laid at his Door. The firſt of theſe hath no Proof but his Conjecture, and the latter is promiſed (none knows when) to be proved by ſome Diſpatches not ſafe to be publiſhed now: But we may be ſure there are no ſuch Diſpatches; otherwiſe, he that dares pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this Libel, hates the <hi>Prince</hi> mortally, and wants Evidence for every thing, would not have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by either Fear or Modeſty, to print ſuch uſeful Teſtimonies as thoſe would have been to his Deſign. His Appeal to Sir <hi>William Temple</hi>'s <hi>Memoirs</hi> we admit, who gives the <hi>Prince</hi> ſo juſt, and yet ſo high a <hi>Character,</hi> that it manifeſts no little Share of Confidence in this Author, to cite ſo unlikely a Book in <hi>juſtification</hi> of thoſe odious Slanders: He begins K. <hi>James</hi> his Reign where it ended, at the <hi>Abdication;</hi> yet his Method is as good as his Chronology, for he makes an old Latin word found in <hi>Feſtus, Livy,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56682:5"/>to be firſt uſed at <hi>Naples</hi> in the laſt Century, hoping to fright us from the Word by the terrible <hi>Exit</hi> of that War; but he conceals that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> to whom this Word was applied, when he ſaw a Conqueror break in upon him, and that he could not ſtay without bringing Ruin upon his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, before his private Flight and Deſertion gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly abſolved all his People from their Oaths of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> and never returned till they unanimouſly recalled him.
<note n="*" place="margin">Guiccardini Hiſtor. l. 1. p. 130.</note> And if the late King had imitated that Prince in his Care of us, when he went away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned for any but himſelf, his peaceable Return had been more likely than now it is.</p>
            <p>But he will prove K.
<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>James</hi> did not deſert, becauſe he was driven from us; and here he conceals that the late King was the Aggreſſor, and had generally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted the Nation by his Attempts on their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberties, and deſpiſing their Petitions for Redreſs: yet theſe were the true Cauſes of the Prince's mighty Succeſs, who had no other, and needed no better Agents than King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Bigotry,</hi> and his Popiſh Counſellors Fury: Theſe prepared <hi>England</hi> to receive a <hi>Deliverer,</hi> and one who would ſee theſe Evils remedied very kindly, and made as many as could, fly to him for <hi>Protection.</hi> And if this true apparent Cauſe had been mentioned, the <hi>Scene</hi> would not appear ſo ſtrange as his Oratory paints it out: theſe deſtructive and dangerous Counſels and Practices of the <hi>Prince's Foes,</hi> did, without a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, force <hi>Proteſtant-Children</hi> to forſake a miſled Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This drove his Servants, the Clergy, and other Subjects, to fly for ſhelter to him who came to their <hi>Reſcue:</hi> But 'tis evident they ſought only their own <hi>Safety,</hi> not the King's <hi>Hurt,</hi> ſince when he was in their Power, none offered any Harm to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56682:5"/>
Well, but he made fair Promiſes to ſome Officers of his Army: and they made as fair Promiſes to him; but they ſaw no Inclination in him to redreſs any thing, unleſs he were compelled to it; and this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged ſome of them to leave him. The Treaty he ſpeaks of, was not moved till he had quitted the Field, and ſaw he could not fight: Yet even then it was accepted by the <hi>Victorious</hi> Prince with all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſincerity, as the Articles he ſent ſhew
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſtor. of Deſert.</hi> p. 91.</note>: To which King <hi>James</hi> promiſed (by Advice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) in the main to agree, the very Night before his firſt departure in Diſguiſe. As to the Danger he was informed of, there was nothing real in it; and the Prince knew nothing of it, as appear'd afterwards when the King was in his Power: and they who knew the <hi>Intrigue,</hi> ſay it was <hi>a Sham,</hi> invented by a Commiſſioner of his own, who knew his Temper, feared his Obſtinacy, and deviſed this to terrify him into an Agreement. But ſuppoſe he were in Danger, that will not prove his Deſertion could not be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, otherwiſe the Mariners in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Ship (<hi>Acts</hi> 27.) might pretend their going off in the Boat was no voluntary Deſertion, ſince they apprehended Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to their Lives by ſtaying. Or thus, A <hi>General</hi> might excuſe leaving his Souldiers, becauſe they Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinied and threatned him. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> did not freely Abdicate, if nothing can be free which is our Choice in a Proſpect of Danger. It is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to a voluntary Act, that there be no Preſſures to incline the Will to one Side: for he who chuſes a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Evil to avoid what he counts a greater, acts volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily. Wherefore if the late King choſe rather to deſert and ſave himſelf, than to ſtay for his Peoples Safety, it was a voluntary Deſertion. This Author ſaith very gently, Upon this the King thought fit to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56682:6"/>withdraw. But impartial Judges muſt call it a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, for the King in the midſt of a Treaty to quit the Kingdom in <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> leaving neither any Deputy or Directions, and this after he had disbanded his Army, diſmiſſed his <hi>Chancellor</hi> and other great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, thrown away the <hi>Great-Seal</hi> into the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> and left his abandoned People to ſhift for themſelves, expoſed to the Inſolence of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble on the one hand, and the worſe Rabble of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded Army on the other hand; this the Parliament called <hi>Abdication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Treaty being thus broke off by King's <hi>James</hi>'s Deſertion,
<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> and the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> (before he was heard of) put into the Prince's Hands, he was at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty whether he would renew the Treaty or no. Yet ſtill he hindred not the King's Return to <hi>London,</hi> where inſtead of going to call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> he burnt all the remaining Writs, and endeavoured to make a <hi>Faction</hi> in the City, by drawing off a Party there from the Prince. Upon which it was neceſſary to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to retire to <hi>Ham,</hi> or ſome other Place near <hi>London,</hi> in order to reaſſume the <hi>Treaty,</hi> and to keep him from doing or receiving any harm. But King <hi>James</hi> who ſtill reſolved to fly rather than treat, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to go to <hi>Ham,</hi> and choſe <hi>Rocheſter</hi> to retire to, ſecretly deſigning for <hi>France,</hi> to raiſe Forces there to expel the <hi>Prince</hi> by Force; ſo that his Meſſages were only to amuſe till he could eſcape; as accordingly he did, ſhipping himſelf a ſecond time for <hi>France,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he came ſafe.</p>
            <p>And now what Occaſion is there for all our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s tragical Outcries,
<note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> of the impriſoning and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating a <hi>Monarch,</hi> who was at Liberty to go where he pleaſed, and not an Hair of his Head hurt? Had that Monarch been Victorious, and the Prince been as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56682:6"/>long and as much in his power, he would ſcarce have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him leave to go back ſafe to <hi>Holland,</hi> but have ſent him out of the way by the Axe, with as little Scruple or Ceremony as he did <hi>Monmouth.</hi> And if his former Dealings with the Prince be conſidered, it muſt be own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he treated him with a Civility more becoming a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Son than a provoked Enemy, and ſhewed (to the Satisfaction of all good <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi>) more of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> than of the <hi>Politician</hi> in this whole Affair: yet this <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> arraigns him for his Charity.</p>
            <p>He accuſes the Prince for ſending him by Water at an unſeaſonable time, thereby endangering his Health; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting that K. <hi>James</hi> went in the Night by Water the very Week before of Choice, when he croſt the River in order to his firſt Attempt to get into <hi>France,</hi> and this without any Damage to his Health; ſo that he uſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as ill as the Prince uſed him. As to his writing to the Biſhops, his ſpeaking to the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> or to Sir <hi>R. Clayton,</hi> or other Citizens; all this is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Fiction; the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> proteſts that no ſuch Propoſition was ever made to him; the ſame is averred by Sir <hi>R. Clayton.</hi> His Letters from <hi>Rocheſter</hi> and <hi>St. Germains,</hi> are full of Wrath and Revenge, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of every one but himſelf, (the firſt Cauſe of all thoſe Evils) and are ſo far from promiſing <hi>Amends,</hi> that they do not own he did any <hi>Fault:</hi> Nor hath the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeen any thing from him ſince, that ſhews his deſire to be reſtored, any other way than by <hi>French Arms,</hi> which he hopes will both force him upon us again, give him opportunity of Revenge, and aſſiſt him in the pious Works of Dragooning and Enſlaving us.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Convention</hi> had declared the Throne void;
<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> and being told that he writ from <hi>St. Germains</hi> in the Stile of a King, they could not receive nor read the Letter writ from thence, which offered no Redreſs, but required an
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56682:7"/>abſolute Submiſſion. Wherefore tho theſe Letters might ſhew his <hi>Deſire</hi> to be in his Throne, they gave no <hi>Hopes</hi> of his taking better Meaſures for the future. He would have ſtaid, if he might have ſet up <hi>Popery,</hi> and ruled us Arbitrarily; and he ſeems not willing to return upon other Terms. Therefore when a King will not govern in a limited <hi>Monarchy,</hi> unleſs he may change it into an abſolute <hi>Empire,</hi> if he deſert with ſuch <hi>Principles,</hi> and continue in them, the <hi>Parliament</hi> judges this to be an <hi>Abdication.</hi> He objects, that by a Maxim of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the Pretences examined,</hi> K. <hi>James</hi> could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: but the Place is not truly cited out of that <hi>Paper,</hi> which rightly ſuppoſes the People of <hi>England</hi> are not willing to part with K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now they have ſworn to protect us, and we to bear Allegiance to them, they are not at liberty to give up their Power; that is, it would be an ill thing in them to leave us now in time of Danger, they cannot do it fairly.
<note n="*" place="margin">Solumid dicimur poſſe face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, quod juſtèſacere poſſumus. <hi>Grat. Gl.</hi> 22 <hi>qu.</hi> 2.</note> And it is ſuppoſed we cannot do that at all, which we cannot do juſtly: Now this rare <hi>Logician</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, Therefore when K. <hi>James</hi> doth deſert, he cannot deſert; tho the People are not unwilling he ſhould go, ſince it was his Mind. But the only true Conſequence of this Maxim is, not that there is any Impoſſibility in the thing, but that he did not well, to chuſe rather to leave us than ſtay and govern by Law. 'Tis true, by disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Army he broke no Statute, but he broke his Oath to protect us, and declared by that Act he would no longer defend us; and then it was time for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbary</hi> and other Lords to ſeek out for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Governour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore this mighty Champion ſings before the <hi>Victory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <hi>Deſertion</hi> ſtill lives, after his Dream of knocking it dead. However, he goes on to cope with another Foe, the <hi>Male Adminiſtration:</hi> And here our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56682:7"/>Author ſays not he is a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the he brags he is an <hi>Engliſh man;</hi> I doubt he is neither, ſince tho Matters are too plain to be denied, and too odious to be juſtified, yet he falls to extenuate and excuſe them with all the <hi>Artifice</hi> that an ill <hi>Cauſe</hi> needs: And hoping to wheedle the Nation with more <hi>Rhetorick</hi> than <hi>Honeſty,</hi> he inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, that <hi>Errors</hi> alone will not juſtify ſuch horrid Crimes as he charges upon this Revolution. And if the <hi>Male-Adminiſtration</hi> were only ſome little Irregularities, and the Revolution ſo horridly wicked as he paints them both, this Aſſertion would be true enough. But in our Caſe the Faults were, taking Methods to deſtroy the Form of Government it ſelf here eſtabliſhed, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon Religion, Liberty, Property; in all which our King is bound by Oath to defend us. Such Faults (when <hi>Petitions</hi> are rejected) muſt be cured ſome way, or a total Ruine muſt follow. And no Hiſtory can ſhew an Inſtance where ſo great Evils were averted without Battel, Noiſe or Executions.</p>
            <p>If I may defend my ſelf againſt an unjuſt and fatal Aſſault, I may begin before I am mortally wounded:
<note place="margin">Page 13.</note> And if we had ſtaid to ſee the Effect of the <hi>Diſpenſing Power, High-Commiſſion-Court,</hi> &amp;c. our unavoidable Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine had been the certain Price for that cautious Delay: The Deſign was as plain, and the Methods as likely as could be; and if no Check had been given by any body, the Event had been e're now as fatally certain, as the Cauſes were evident. It muſt be granted K. <hi>James</hi> is a zealous Catholick, and hath a Paſſion for the French Government; and therefore why ſhould we not believe his aiming at eſtabliſhing Popery, and the French way of Governing, proceeded from his own Inclinations? Or if his Miniſters put him upon theſe <hi>Projects,</hi> (as he inſinuates) ſince he would let none of them be called to Account, it was all one to the Sufferers whether he or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56682:8"/>his Miniſters deviſed their Ruine. Again, he requires ſome Author's Name to the Particulars charged upon K. <hi>James</hi>'s Government; but the Charge is ſo true, and known to ſo many thouſands, that there is more need to inquire into his Name that dares to outface a whole Nation: for if his Authority be not more weighty than his Excuſes, he will never carry his Point.</p>
            <p>The examining of Particulars will ſhew this;
<note place="margin">Page 14.</note> ſome of them he denies, extenuates the reſt, and varniſhes all over. But (1.) were there no Severities in the <hi>West?</hi> Yes, he grants it, and ſeems ſorry for it, but ſays they were Rebels, and had forfeited their Lives and Eſtates. Let that be granted; yet ſtill there have been greater Rebellions in former Reigns, yet no King (after the Danger was over, and the Party broken) did ever exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſo many of his deluded Subjects in cold Blood: None were condemned upon their bare Confeſſion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted with aſſurance of Pardon, nor hanged up with Healths drank, and Huzza's. He throws all this upon the Miniſters: but we have not forgot the Triumphs at <hi>White-Hall</hi> upon the News of theſe Barbarities, which K. <hi>James</hi> himſelf repeated to the Foreign Miniſters with much Joy, and called that bloody Circuit, <hi>Jefferies his Campaign:</hi> Nor how that Butcher was put into the King's Boſom, and advanced for executing theſe merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Orders he had received. <hi>Pollexfen</hi> was only put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Commiſſion, to grace the bloody Scene with ſome Colour of Law, of which heavy Imployment he acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf ſo well, that Complaints were made of him: And this Government promoted him only for his Skill to a Poſt where there were no Lives concerned. The bloody Temper of <hi>Kirk</hi> could not recommend him to K. <hi>William,</hi> whoſe Life, as well as his Reign here, ſhew, he is merciful perhaps to exceſs.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56682:8"/>
(2.) That illegal and terrible High-Commiſſion, ſet up to trample upon Law, to turn out all honeſt Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and put Popiſh Prieſts in their places, to Fine, Impriſon, Baniſh, and what not, the Innocent as well as the Guilty; this is haſtily paſſed over with this ſorry Excuſe, that one of the Actors in it is now after four Years, but only in a fair way to be preferr'd by K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> and this too after begging Pardon for his Faults.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) He catches at the word <hi>[all],</hi> and denies that all good Proteſtants were turned out, and that all Places of Truſt and Profit were filled with unqualified Men. But the Phraſe may be juſtified, ſince tho ſome who called themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> kept their Places, yet they could neither be zealous for, nor ſound in that <hi>Religion,</hi> who promiſed to comply with a Catholick King in all the <hi>Methods</hi> he took to deſtroy it. And if any one of them ſcrupled at any thing, immediately he was caſhiered, and an unqualified Man generally put in his Place. All that he can ſay to the reſt in a Lump, is, That the E. of <hi>S.</hi> and L. <hi>C.</hi> forced K. <hi>James</hi> againſt his own Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to prefer Father <hi>Peters</hi> to the Privy-Council, to model the Iriſh Army and Government, to elect <hi>Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi>-College-Fellows, to regulate Corporations, cloſet Gentlemen, and to impriſon and try the Biſhops. Well, Engliſh Men are good-natured, and muſt believe King <hi>James</hi> had no Zeal for Popery, no Love for Father <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> no Deſire to get a Popiſh Army, no hankering af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> no Intent to have a Parliament pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingag'd to take off <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> no purpoſe to bring <hi>Friars</hi> into Colleges and Churches, no Anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops for petitioning—<hi>Riſum teneatis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici.</hi> Alas, he was trick'd into all this by the P. of <hi>O.</hi> his truſty Agents, and poor Gentleman never ſmelt the Plot: He had many Catholicks in his Court and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56682:9"/>but never heard or truſted any of them, but was wholly guided by pretended <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>— But if any be ſo void of common Senſe, as to believe and admit this Stuff, yet it muſt be granted this unlucky Apologiſt throws more Dirt upon K. <hi>James</hi> than he wipes off; and to make him ſeem innocent, deſcribes him as the eaſieſt and moſt unthinking Creature alive, pretending he was drawn in by two bantring <hi>Sycophants</hi> to do the moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Acts, and the moſt ungrateful to his People, and all this againſt his own Inclinations as well as true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt: Were this true, he might be indicted as a <hi>Non Compos,</hi> and his Capacity to govern queſtioned; but being horribly falſe, it will follow, the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were in danger of loſing the Liberties and Religion by a <hi>Prince</hi> of ſuch a Temper, ſuch Inclinations, and one that was ſet upon ſuch deſtructive <hi>Methods.</hi> And thus our Excuſer runs upon one Rock to avoid another, and can no way bring his Maſter off ſafe.</p>
            <p>Yet he goes on,
<note place="margin">Page 15.</note> without bluſhing, to call K. <hi>James</hi>'s Heat to advance <hi>Popery,</hi> nothing but the natural and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy Paſſion of ſhewing ſome little Favour to them of his own Religion.—And feigns that two Lords, hired by the P. of <hi>O.</hi> forced him to do that which above all things he deſired. Now I wonder this Prince ſhould be ſo prodigal of his Mony, to ſquander it away upon Agents, to perſwade a Man to gratify himſelf, to drive him on to that, which his Prieſts would certainly make him do <hi>gratis.</hi> He thinks we never heard how K. <hi>James</hi> led F. <hi>Peters</hi> into the Council by the Hand, and made a Speech in his Commendation to that Board; or he durſt not ſay he was averſe to his Admiſſion into the Council. We know he was the firſt Adviſer and Promoter of <hi>Quo Warranto's</hi> in his Brother's time, and furiouſly drove on <hi>Regulations</hi> in his own. And doth this Dauber think to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56682:9"/>prove K. <hi>James</hi> was againſt thoſe Meaſures, by his tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling an eaſy Peer, (who had drudged for him in that vile Imployment) that theſe Methods were againſt his Judgment: If he did ſay this, it was <hi>Proteſtatio contra Factum,</hi> and ſhews the Credulity of the Peer, not the Sincerity of that Prince, who had convinced Mankind, that to ſerve <hi>a Turn,</hi> he could ſay one thing, and mean another. His Proof from ſome Mens Brags ſince the Revolution, is equally weak, becauſe when Reputation or Intereſt alone are conſidered, many will boaſt of more than they ever really performed; nor did I ever hear that any one has boaſted of this. But (he ſaith) the Prince promiſed divers Places here before he ſet out from <hi>Holland;</hi> and this he takes for an infallible proof that he aimed then at the <hi>Crown:</hi> But it muſt be noted that he came to redreſs Grievances, and eſpecially the filling Places with unqualified Men; ſo that if the Treaty had gone on, and K. <hi>James</hi> ſtayed, many places muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be made void. And he who had done the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Service, might juſtly expect the Favour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend ſome of his Friends to thoſe <hi>Vacancies,</hi> tho he never expected to be King of <hi>England.</hi> But beſides all this, it is poſitively affirmed that no ſuch Promiſes were made to any Perſons; ſome were diſguſted, others quite loſt, becauſe no ſuch Promiſes were made to them. As for his Order to the French Ambaſſador to depart the Kingdom, this was not till the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> was put into his Hands; and the Truſt repoſed in him; required him to diſcharge one who was likely to be a Spye upon his Counſels, and one whoſe Intereſt it was to betray him, and hinder the Nation's Settlement.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Parallel</hi> is yet a bolder Step than his <hi>Apology,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 16.</note> for he undertakes to ſhew K. <hi>William</hi> to be as guilty of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government as K. <hi>James.</hi> And firſt he ſaith, his <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56682:10"/>to Arbitrary Rule are as great as the late King's, becauſe K. <hi>William</hi> ſent a Meſſage to the <hi>Parliament</hi> not to put too many Limits upon the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> leſt they forced him to leave us. But as no ſuch Meſſage was ever ſent, ſo ſuppoſe it had been, is this Check to the <hi>Republicans,</hi> ſo arbitrary as K. <hi>James</hi>'s declaring he would have no Bounds ſet to the <hi>Prerogative</hi> but his Will, and his conſtant Actings accordingly? For he told his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es what he would have to be Law, but this King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of his Judges what they think legal. He grants, the late King uſed a <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> and that too in other Inſtances beſides <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> which Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty our Author (contrary to the Opinion of his Friend K. <hi>Lewis</hi>) calls, <hi>That deſirable and neceſſary Good of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi>—Well, let it be ſo, where then is the <hi>Parallel?</hi> Why K. <hi>James</hi> granted this againſt Law, and without a <hi>Parliament;</hi> and K. <hi>William</hi> grants the ſame Liberty, not by a <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> or by <hi>Prerogative,</hi> but by <hi>Parliament:</hi> (that is) K. <hi>James</hi> he granted it arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, K. <hi>William</hi> ſettles it by Law.—A moſt exact Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel no doubt, and a good proof of K. <hi>William</hi>'s Deſign to be arbitrary. To get off this Difficulty, the Prince's Agents are topt upon us again, and all the blame laid on him and them; they managed poor K. <hi>James</hi> with inviſible Wires, who followed them blindfold to his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. And if he were ſo eaſily wheedled by corrupted <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> may he not more eaſily be wheedled into il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal Acts by fierce and dangerous <hi>Papiſts?</hi> And is it not then our wiſeſt way never to wiſh for the return of a Prince ſo apt to be miſled? If he be in the beſt Humour in the World with the Biſhops upon his Reſtauration, how ſoon may ſome <hi>Popiſh Emiſſary</hi> incenſe him once more againſt them, and run them again into the Tower, and from thence to the Bar?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56682:10"/>
It was truly urged againſt King <hi>James,</hi> that his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Catholicks was too ſtrong for the Law: And he will prove King <hi>William</hi> guilty of the ſame Crime, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in time of War he hires a few Foreign Papiſts into his Army, Men who ſtay no where, have no Intereſt to ſerve, no Deſign but on their Pay, and no Concern a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Religion of any Countrey which employs them; which with inexpreſſibly <hi>Effrontery</hi> (he ſaith) is worſe than K. <hi>James Caſhiering</hi> (in Times of Peace) great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Military and Civil Proteſtant Officers, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Engliſh and Iriſh Papiſts in their Places, whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt obliged and inclined them, to aſſiſt their King in changing the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> of their <hi>Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> Again, he asks if <hi>Catholicks</hi> (ſo he calls them falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in moſt places, not Roman Catholicks) be not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced as much, and do not exerciſe their Religion as freely now as ever. I reply, they are permitted, but not at all countenanced. Do their Fryars walk in their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits? Do they ring Bells, and invite all People to ſee and hear their Foppery? or make publick Shews? Are they promoted to Churches and Colleges, and to be <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy-Counſellors?</hi> If not, how abſurd is his Query? and where is his <hi>Parallel?</hi> But he fancies we were ſafer when his Catholicks held their Liberty meerly by the <hi>Favour</hi> of Engliſh Proteſtants, (that is, ſurely he means in King <hi>James</hi> his Time) than now when <hi>Foreign Princes</hi> of the Romiſh Communion deſire this King to tolerate them. Now I dare appeal to the Papiſts, Whether they did not believe it was King <hi>James,</hi> not Engliſh Proteſtants, who gave them the Liberty in that Reign? And whether they did not think their <hi>Religion</hi> more likely to be reſtored by a <hi>Prince</hi> of their own <hi>Faith</hi> in League with <hi>France,</hi> than by a Proteſtant King, Confederate with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria?</hi> And if they think their Religion likely to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56682:11"/>reſtored by King <hi>William,</hi> let them make it evident by fighting for him againſt the late King and his French Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, otherwiſe all theſe Suggeſtions are as groundleſs as they are malicious.</p>
            <p>Yet upon a review of theſe Bug-Bears of his own dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up,
<note place="margin">Pag. 18.</note> he is terribly affrighted, and falls to pray to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert theſe imaginary Evils; uſing at the ſame time all his <hi>Rhetorical Amplifications</hi> to excite us to run into certain and real Miſchiefs, by deſtroying this Government, that can and will defend our Religion and Civil-Rights, to ſet up another which will deſtroy both. But the Cheat is ſo viſible, and his Parallels ſo ridiculous, that no Man of Senſe can be deluded by ſuch Stuff. Wherefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Point, and have ſhewed that King <hi>James</hi> was the Aggreſſor, and hurt himſelf: we injured no Body, and only warded off the Blow which aimed at the very Vitals of our Church, and our Ancient Government; and which would have turned it from a Limited to an Abſolute Monarchy; a Change infinitetly worſe for this <hi>Nation</hi> than our Author can pretend hath been made by this <hi>Revolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which brings me to his ſecond Pretence for reſtoring King <hi>James,
<note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> viz.</hi> the ſettling the Government upon its old <hi>Baſts.</hi> And here, while he ſeems to cite a long Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of his Adverſary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, <hi>p.</hi> 10.</note> he jumbles the Senſe, alters the Phraſes, puts in his own Comment, and leaves out ſome of the Author's Words; and then accuſes the Writer (whom he blindly and falſly gueſſes to be the Earl of <hi>Nottingham</hi>) of Ignorance, in the Hiſtory and Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> want of Judgment, Diſingenuity, Impudence, and what not? But it will be eaſily proved, to all that know that accompliſhed <hi>Peer,</hi> and read this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, this is not his Lordſhip's, but this Libeller's own <hi>Character.</hi> And his Reply to this Paſſage, confirms the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56682:11"/>Obſervation; for he owns that the <hi>Convention</hi> declared the <hi>Throne</hi> void; therefore he miſtakes in ſaying they made it void. Declaring, ſuppoſes a thing done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and he may as well charge a Judg with committing that <hi>Fact</hi> which he declares to be <hi>Treaſon,</hi> as to ſay the Convention made the <hi>Throne</hi> void. But we utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his infallible Mark, <hi>viz.</hi> That a <hi>Vacancy</hi> certainly proves a <hi>Monarchy</hi> Elective, and that in an Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy the Throne cannot be without a <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor</hi> one Moment. For <hi>Scotland</hi> is, and ever was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to be no Elective, but an Hereditary Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; yet upon the Death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> there was a Vacancy for above five Years, while the Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Titles of ſix ſeveral Pretenders were under Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. And there was a Vacancy in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Spotſw. <hi>Hiſtory of</hi> Scotland, <hi>An.</hi> 1279.</note> from the two and twentieth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> the Third was ſlain, till <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh was declared King. Yea, there was more than a Moment between the Reſignation of <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and the Entrance of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth. I grant, that where there is no Doubt (concerning the next Heir) upon Ceſſion or Death, there the right Heir ſucceeds immediately: But while the next Heir is ambiguous in an Hereditary Monarchy, till the Title be examined, cleared and declared, none of the Pretenders can aſſume the Royal Dignity. And his other Maxim of our Kings never dying, is not literally true in any other Caſe, but where there is a certain, known and undoubted Heir. So that an enquiry into, and declaring the right Heir, doth not make an Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy Elective. But he denies that the preſent Queen was the right Heir; and here he ſets up his Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and hectors his Adverſary, the Convention, and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> for not proving the Prince of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56682:12"/>
               <hi>Wales</hi> Suppoſititious. Now he neither proves it a real Birth himſelf, nor anſwers half the Arguments have been urged againſt it; yet is very angry that others will not prove a Negative.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Convention</hi> had ſeen the Depoſitions,
<note place="margin">Pag. 20.</note> knew the Credit of the Witneſſes, and all the Circumſtances of the Delivery, yet after all did not believe it a real <hi>Birth;</hi> they had examined it as far as was neceſſary to their own Satisfaction, and after all declared the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange</hi> to be the right Heir. The Papiſts, (whoſe Religion was to be brought in by the Father, and eſtabliſhed by this pretended Son) and all their Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhers ſhould have brought better Proof of their New Heir, than a few depending, partial, intereſted Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; it was their Buſineſs to have produced their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The Convention judged according to all the Proofs they had, and unanimouſly declared for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs's Right; who being the next Heir, in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the Opinion of the whole Nation, (ſome few excepted) they ſufficiently ſhewed they did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make this Monarchy Elective, in that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the true Heir (as they verily believed) to be Queen. But ſuppoſe they had ſpent Months or Years in the Inquiry, and left the Nation to ſink in the mean while, what would all this have ſignified to Jeſuits, and Noſe-led Proteſtants? Unleſs they had pronounced for the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> right or wrong, this ſort of People would not have acquieſced in their Determination; and therefore they did wiſely, after they, and almoſt the whole Body of Engliſh Proteſtants were ſatisfied, not to trouble themſelves any further.</p>
            <p>Beſides,
<note place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> if King <hi>James</hi> did believe it, why did he not put it upon a Trial in Parliament in his own Time? He underſtood the People of <hi>England</hi> generally ſuſpected
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56682:12"/>there was Artifice uſed to exclude a Proteſtant Heir; and therefore why did he not call a Parliament long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came over, and ſubmit it to their Inquiry? Yea, when the Prince was come, He, the Biſhops, Nobility and Officers, yea all <hi>England</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red King <hi>James</hi> to call a Parliament to ſettle this and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Matters, yet he would not call one, but fled from this way of Trial. If it be ſaid, King <hi>James</hi> had proved it by the Depoſitions; 'tis anſwered, Theſe were Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes all of one ſide, choſen by a Party, ſworn before partial Men, and in too private a Place for an Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy. The People doubting about the true Heir, ought to have Satisfaction given to their <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives</hi> in Parliament, which was not done: yea, King <hi>James</hi> did not call theſe Witneſſes till fourteen Days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prince landed, <hi>viz. October</hi> 22. thereby ſhewing he did not intend to give the Nation any ſort of Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but Fear, and the ſerving a Turn, extorted this Condeſcenſion from him. Wherefore when King <hi>James</hi> would not try this Matter by his Parliament, when he might have done it, why ſhould the <hi>Convention</hi> do his Buſineſs for him, and neglect the Nation's Safety? But he urges, that none were denied Satisfaction who deſired it: I reply, the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> formerly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe had not the Satisfaction given her which was fit, and it is generally believed ſhe was ſent out of the way on purpoſe: The Dutch Embaſſador (who ought to have ſatisfied Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi>) was not called, the Biſhops by deſign were ſent to the Tower, the good Proteſtants were all at Church; and this lucky Juncture, with a Place ſuddenly reſolved on, ſeem plainly deſigned for Privacy: And indeed none were at the Birth it ſelf but intereſted Friends, and Well-wiſhers to a Popiſh Heir, whoſe Deſign and Hopes made ſome of them willing to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56682:13"/>affirm, and others eaſy to believe any thing. Nor is the late Daughter's Birth among <hi>Foreigners,</hi> and ſuch as would top this Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> upon us, a ſufficient Evidence that a Son was born before; the Reckoners there were as often ſhifted as they had been here, and as few Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were called: and after all the Letters that were writ hither, and after all the Promiſes of a Birth that ſhould be ſo well atteſted as to confirm the former, the one was managed as much in the dark as the other had been; nor have we yet heard of any of thoſe Atteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with which we were ſo much threatned.</p>
            <p>Having therefore not proved a Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 22.</note> the Argument from his Innocency and the Injury done him, falls, <hi>Non entis nulla ſunt Accidentia.</hi> Had the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion believed there was ſuch a Son, they would have owned him as Heir; but believing there was no ſuch Perſon, they cannot properly be ſaid to intend or do him any Injury. Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reſolution to have the Prince joined with her, is known to many: The Injury done to Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> and her Children is none at all, but a Benefit; for what was her Title or theirs worth, if the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had permitted the Papiſts to ſet up a Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and perhaps Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to exclude them all for ever? Is not her Succeſſion and her Iſſues, both nearer and ſurer than it was under King <hi>James?</hi> King <hi>William,</hi> it's true, is made King for his Life; but if he die before the Queen, (which the Hazards he runs in defending both Siſters Titles, makes too probable) then the Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> and her Children have no Injury at all: and if he ſhould ſurvive Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> I appeal to any impartial Man, whether this King who reſcued the Princeſs's Title from being extinguiſhed, do not merit to keep the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> for the reſt of his Life, eſpecially ſince ſhe and her Heirs precede his by any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56682:13"/>other Wife? From <hi>Aggravations</hi> he falls to <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and while he blames his Adverſaries Ignorance therein, he evidently ſhews his own, in affirming, that no ſuch Breach was ever made in our Engliſh Succeſſion before. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we have had but 27 Reigns from the Conqueſt to this Revolution, and in that time there have been ſeveral Breaches in the Succeſſion, moſt of them greater than this, <hi>viz. William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>William Rufus, Henry</hi> the Firſt, King <hi>Stephen,</hi> King <hi>John, Henry</hi> the Fourth and Seventh; to which ſome (who deny <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th's Marriage with his Brother's Widow to be lawful) add Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and the Papiſts put in Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Now upon ſuch Breaches, the Sentence of the People was had to confirm the Pretender's Title, yet this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtill remained <hi>Hereditary,</hi> in common Account, and never was reckoned (as by his Argument it would have been) an <hi>Elective Monarchy.</hi> But to keep to his Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there was a greater Breach than is now, by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's coming to the Crown; for though <hi>Richard</hi> the Third was ſlain, and left no Child, yet he left an Heireſs, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Daughter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth; and ſome of her Siſters were then alive, as was alſo a Son and a Daughter of <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> all of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> to whom the Right of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion certainly belonged: yet <hi>Henry</hi> was crowned in <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1485, and aſſumed the Crown in Right of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bacon<hi>'s Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of</hi> Hen. 7. p. 6, &amp; 11</note> and when he did marry the Heireſs of <hi>York,</hi> he would not ſuffer her Title to be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor allow the Parliament to ſettle the Crown any further than on his own Heirs. So that here were four or five Perſons excluded at his aſſuming the Crown, and no Care taken of them in the Settlement afterwards: Yet ſtill the Monarchy remained Hereditary.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56682:14"/>
His Adverſary did not inſtance in <hi>Edward</hi> the Third,
<note place="margin">Page 23.</note> becauſe the only Breach then was in the Perſon of the reigning King; but then he was worſe dealt with than the late King, being forced to reſign firſt his Crown, and ſoon after his Life, and to thank his Depoſers for decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the next in Succeſſion King. But in <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth's Caſe there were great Breaches made, which he would conceal by ſaying, King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second left no Son, and by falſly affirming, <hi>Henry</hi> was the next Heir, becauſe the Pretences of the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> were not yet ſet on foot. But the Truth is, King <hi>Richard</hi>'s right Heirs were the <hi>Mortimers</hi> deſcended from a Daughter of <hi>Lio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> elder Brother to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth's Father: And <hi>Edmund Mortimer</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> his Siſter <hi>Ann,</hi> (by whom came after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the true Title to the Houſe of <hi>York</hi>) and <hi>Elianor,</hi> were then and long after all alive, and utterly excluded, when <hi>Henry</hi> aſſumed the Crown, though the Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle</hi> in open Parliament declared, that <hi>Edmund</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid was true and undoubted Heir to the Crown. So that here was the reigning King depoſed and murdered, a remote Branch of the Royal Family advanced, and four Princes of the Blood, with their future Iſſue, excluded from their Right, and kept out for three Reigns: Which is a much greater Breach than is now; and our Author's Outcry for a <hi>Parallel</hi> ſhews his Ignorance or his Diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. We can ſhew him Acts of Parliament, which have not only excluded the Collateral Line, but the right Heirs, even when they were not (as it is in our Caſe) of a Religion different from the eſtabliſhed one, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Safety of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort,
<note place="margin">Page 24.</note> conſidering the Reaſon and Neceſſity, our <hi>Revolution</hi> hath made the leaſt Breach that ever was made in ſuch a Change. The late King was not depoſed, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56682:14"/>deſerted us; his next Heir (the preſent Queen) of whom there is no doubt, was put into the <hi>Vacant Throne,</hi> and the Crown ſettled Hereditarily upon her and her Siſter, and their Heirs ſucceſſively: there is no Breach made at all, except one Contingency happen; and if it do, 'tis Perſonal, Temporary, and highly-merited: and if great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Breaches never made this Monarchy Elective, this leſſer one cannot do it. The Succeſſion is taken due Care of in the right Line, as the Convention believes, and ſettled on the true Heirs; ſo that they were no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicans,</hi> but true Friends of the Old Engliſh Monarchy, which the People of <hi>England</hi> (I hope) will never change for French Slavery, the certain Conſequent of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration into which he would decoy us.</p>
            <p>The next Bugbear he ſets up to fright us into Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt the preſent King, is the Fear that the Title of <hi>Conquest</hi> ſhould alter the Government. But by the way, ſince the late King cannot return but by Force, is there not more danger that he proving victorious, ſhould urge this Title in prejudice of our Liberties, who was ſo arbitrary when he was here? And if ſo, we leap out of the Frying-pan into the Fire, by his recovering his Throne. King <hi>William</hi> I am ſure never pleaded this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, nor do either of the Authors he cites, maintain that he conquered the People of <hi>England,</hi> (though in Fact he did conquer the late King.) We freely ſubmitted to him, and he as freely ſwore to govern us by our Laws. Which one Obſervation ſpoils all his impertinent Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation upon the Miſchiefs of Conqueſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Slavery, Loſs of the Subjects Rights and Properties, and Change of Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sure he is dreaming of ſome wretched Country, conquered and ruled by the moſt Unchriſtian King. Our Prince treats his very Enemies who ſtay here, better than King <hi>Lewis</hi> doth his own Subjects: and the Conqueſt thoſe Authors ſpeak of, relating only to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56682:15"/>late King, is very conſiſtent, (1.) with the Prince's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration; (2.) with the Convention ſettling the Crown on him; and (3.) with our Rights and Freedom.</p>
            <p>When the Prince put out his Declaration,
<note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> he could not foreſee King <hi>James</hi> would finally refuſe to call a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; or that he ſhould firſt reſolve to fight, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conquered, to fly rather than to treat. He brought no more Force with him than ſufficed to protect himſelf, and the Engliſh who joined with him, in requiring their Grievances might be redreſſed: which ſhews he did not aim at Conqueſt. Yea, when the late King's Army was routed and disbanded, he yielded to treat, according to his Declaration; which ſhewed no Deſign to take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage as a Conqueror. And when the late King fled from this Treaty, he did not meddle either with the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration or the Crown, till they were ſucceſſively offered him by thoſe who repreſented the People of <hi>England,</hi> and he granted them all their Liberties at firſt; and ſince he hath had Power, he hath redreſſed all the Grievances, which the Trouble his Enemies give him will permit him to help: nor hath he refuſed any Acts of this kind which the Parliament hath offered him. So that as far as he could then foreſee, his Promiſes in his Declaration and his Actions do agree. He might ſafely ſay he came not for the <hi>Crown;</hi> but did not ſay he would not accept it, if there were no body elſe to wear it, or if it were freely offered him. And as to the Convention's Gift, they and King <hi>William</hi> believe, after the Throne was vacant, that they ought to have declared his Wife's Hereditary Right. As to himſelf, he will own that the Crown was the juſt Gift of a free and grateful People, who ſo little believe his having infringed their Liberties, (as Conquerors uſe to do) that I dare ſay, if it were needful, the Parliament would add any further Confirmation to his Title. Nor will the Body of the Engliſh Nation ſuffer a Mercenary
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56682:15"/>Pen, hired with a few Luidores, to alienate their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from ſo kind and gracious a Prince, who perhaps might have ſeized the Crown by his Power, but choſe to accept it in his dear Conſort's Right, and as a Reward of his perſonal Services; and never did bear himſelf like a Conqueror, or treat us like a conquered People.</p>
            <p>His Declamation upon the woful Condition of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Nation, the Value of our Liberties,
<note place="margin">Page 26.</note> and the Zeal other People have ſhewed, and we ought to ſhew to ſhake off Slavery and Arbitrary Power, I highly approve, and would have tranſcribed it, had it not been too long, being a juſt Satyr upon King <hi>James</hi> his Effects to rule us Arbitrarily, a true Deſcription of the miſerable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poor <hi>French,</hi> who, as he grants, <hi>pag.</hi> 54. are all made Slaves. And truly this whole Diſcourſe is uſeful, both as it arms us againſt our late Arbitrary Monarch's freſh Attempts by that Tyrant's Aſſiſtance, and as it is a clear Vindication of the late Revolution, and a deſerved <hi>Encomium</hi> on thoſe brave Engliſh-men, who after the Example of their Anceſtors, nobly ſhook off the Shackles K. <hi>James</hi> was putting on them.</p>
            <p>However,
<note place="margin">Page 27.</note> this can be no Motive to any body to rebel againſt K. <hi>William,</hi> who, as this Enemy confeſſes, never yet pretended to this Title of <hi>Conquest,</hi> and knows nothing what Books his Secretary licenſes: and that Book which moves this Author's Jealouſy, ſpeaks only of a Conqueſt over K. <hi>James,</hi> not over the People of <hi>England:</hi> ſo that it makes nothing to his purpoſe. K. <hi>William,</hi> as his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for <hi>Scotland</hi> aſſures us, came to hinder the late King from taking away his Subjects Liberties: and it was high time, when that King in his Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience in <hi>Scotland, Feb.</hi> 12. 1686. ſaid, (in the very Phraſe of the French Tyrant) <hi>he would have his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power obeyed without reſerve,</hi>—<q>and made them ſwear to aſſiſt and defend him and his Heirs in the exerciſe of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56682:16"/>this his abſolute Power againſt all Deadly.</q> Now he that claims abſolute Power, and Obedience to it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſerve, leaves his Subjects no Liberties; he owns that his Will is not bounded by Laws or Priviledges, and no Law can exempt a Subject in that caſe from obeying an illegal Command.—Yea, he makes that enſlaved Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſwear to put this heavy Yoke on their own Necks, and to help him to deſtroy all that ſtood up for their Laws and Liberties. And they were following this Copy in <hi>England,</hi> when <hi>Jefferies</hi> would ſuffer no Lawyer to plead in the High-Commiſſion-Court; and without hearing the Cauſe, gave Sentence in theſe Words, <hi>It is the King's Pleaſure that ſuch and ſuch be ſuſpended, fined, deprived,</hi> &amp;c. And the late King himſelf at <hi>Oxford</hi> would not hear the <hi>Magdalen-Fellows</hi> plead their Cauſe, but in a Fury told them, <hi>He would make them know he was their King, and would be obeyed.</hi> Now let this Gentleman declaim as much as he will againſt a King's infringing his Peoples Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, it hurts not K. <hi>William,</hi> but falls very heavy upon his own Maſter.</p>
            <p>And ſo doth this eloquent Deſcription of the Miſchief of a Prince's aſſuming a Diſpenſing Power,
<note place="margin">Page 28.</note> which fatally threatens the Liberties of a People, and (as he ſaith) makes them Tenants at Will for their Privileges, wherein the Law gives them a Freehold. And was it not time for the Engliſh to look about them, when the late King claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and exerciſed this Power in a thouſand Inſtances? But to avoid that natural Application, he pretends to wonder that our Convention and Parliament ſince the Revolution never ſet Bounds between the Prerogative and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Rights—Which is a notorious piece of Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for he knows when the Convention tendred the Crown to their Majeſties, in that very Declaration ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly approved, <hi>Feb.</hi> 12. 1688. theſe Bounds are ſet, and the Subjects Liberties and Rights declared, (eſpecially
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56682:16"/>ſuch as the late King had invaded) to which K. <hi>William</hi> conſented: and this was enrolled both in the Parliament-Rolls, and in the Chancery
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion,</hi> p. 127.</note>. Yea, this Author cites this Declaration three or four times by name, 33, 34, 35. yet here he would inſinuate there was no ſuch thing, only that he may ſlander the preſent King and Parliament. With equal Confidence he accuſes K. <hi>William,</hi> upon the Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for acting Arbitrarily, becauſe to ſpare the Effuſion of his Subjects Blood, he granted ſome Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges to the Iriſh who laid down their Arms, by his own Authority, tho he confeſſes he got them afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliament: Which is no more Power than a General is often wont to aſſume, in ſigning Capitulations without conſulting his Prince. And is this Criminal in a King, that is allowable in ſome of his Officers? He knows the late King in time of Peace granted both Privileges and Diſpenſations more contrary to Law, and deſpiſed a Parliament's Confirmation, affirming his Will to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Authority for the moſt illegal Grants. From this he paſſes to harangue upon the Injuſtice of <hi>illegal Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Worth of <hi>Freedom,</hi> which he ſets off as the choiceſt part of our <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> forgetting that K. <hi>James,</hi> contrary to Law, impriſoned many hundreds in all parts of <hi>England</hi> upon <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Invaſion; and clapt up ſeven Biſhops, Peers of the Realm, moſt unjuſtly, and almoſt daily broke in upon this dear Piece of our Engliſh Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges in time of Peace.</p>
            <p>But he that excuſes this, and will not ſee it,
<note place="margin">Pag. 29.</note> roars out at our preſent King for clapping up a few <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and aggravates the Matter extreamly, but ſaith not one word of the Occaſion. But 'tis well known, that while the French King and King <hi>James</hi> prepare to invade us from without, the Papiſts, and their Proteſtant Accomplices of that Party, have laid divers treaſonable Plots at home to deſtroy this Government; and by railing, by Libels, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56682:17"/>all other Methods, have laboured to diſturb the publick Peace, to ſeduce their Majeſties Subjects from their <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,</hi> and to take away their Majeſties Lives and Crowns: for which under any Government but this, many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of them e're now had paid their Heads: But our Prince, who, like the brave <hi>Antoninus, puniſhes all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> more gently than the Law ordains
<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Jul. Capitolin. in Vitâ, <hi>pag.</hi> 206.</note>, hath been content only to confine ſome of the chief of them to prevent their doing Miſchief, as the Safety of the Nation abſolutely requires when <hi>Invaſion</hi> was threatned; and this is the Occaſion of all this Noiſe. As for the Benefit of <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> which he ſaith they were denied, I muſt obſerve they were Men (generally) that deſerved no Protection from, or Benefit by the Laws, becauſe they have not only refuſed to ſwear <hi>Allegiance</hi> to this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but by Words and Actions, declared, they are ſworn Enemies to it, and reſolve to overturn it as ſoon as they can: Nor could the Government want In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations againſt them, who had ſo often and openly diſcovered their Intentions. But it was K. <hi>William</hi> his innate Clemency (which would ſoften any but ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Creatures) that made him forbid any Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And moſt of theſe Men were ſet at Liberty ſo ſoon, that his Majeſty's Friends thought his good Nature pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over that Caution which ſeemed neceſſary while ſo many Plots had been laid, and were actually carrying on: Yea one of them, upon whom actual Treaſon in the higheſt Degree was proved, hath been pardoned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conviction and Condemnation; and of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds guilty of Treaſon, two only have ſuffered for it in this Reign; yet he rails at the Parliament for ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Hubeas Gorpus</hi> Act; as if this were betraying their Truſt, and giving up all our Liberties: Whereas, firſt, they had full Power and Right to ſuſpend an Act made by the ſame Body not many Years ago. And, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56682:17"/>there was Reaſon, yea, Neceſſity to ſuſpend it then, when the French were about to invade us, and ſo many ill Men at Land ready to join them: The Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of which unnatural Deſign of betraying his Native Country, is the true Cauſe why this Writer: (one of the Criminals) falls into a Rage like that of the evil Spirit in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.29. who counted it a Torment not to be ſuffered to do Miſchief: For they who would bring in that King by Force, that without any Parliament ſuſpended all Laws, cannot be concerned for Engliſh Laws or Liberties: But as one of the Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices writ to the French King in a Letter that was ſeized, their being in Priſon made it impoſſible for them to ſerve him as they deſired.</p>
            <p>The raving Fit holds him all the next Page,
<note place="margin">Page 30.</note> wherein with much Fury, and no Senſe, he inveighs againſt the Parliament, who had full Power to repeal this Act, only for ſuſpending it till the Danger was over, and as it proves, it was pity this Author was kept in Priſon, and hindred from appearing in Arms, for then he would have had his Deſert e're now, and this Libel had been ſtrangled in the Birth. I am ſure all good Subjects of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have their Liberty, and had during the Suſpenſion of that Act: none but Rebels and Plotters, Enemies to the Government, and ſuch as renounce its Protection can complain. And if theſe bloody Men had been let looſe, the Parliament had betrayed the Liberties of all the King's peaceable Subjects, and ſacrificed many of their Lives, and the Government had not protected thoſe who bear true Faith and Allegiance to it. Yet he hath one true Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in his Anger, <hi>viz.</hi> That K. <hi>James</hi> never dream'd of ſuch a Method; No, for he hang'd up the Innocent with the Guilty, he proclaim'd divers Peers and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Traitors, for intending to join with <hi>Monmouth</hi> after he was defeated. My Lord <hi>Macclesfield</hi>'s, <hi>Brandon Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi>'s,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56682:18"/>
               <hi>Delamere</hi>'s, and others Caſes are not forgot. He ſcorn'd to play at the ſmall Game of ſuſpending one Law for a few Months on juſt Reaſon in a legal way; he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Parliament ſuſpended what Laws he pleaſed for ever: And can it be the way to ſecure our Liberties, to ſend for this Prince again?</p>
            <p>He in times of Peace caſhiered all Officers and Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that were qualified,
<note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> and got a whole Army of unqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Tories in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and put out moſt of the qualified Officers, filling their Places with illegal Men here: yet this Writer (who hath the Forehead to excuſe all this) arraigns K. <hi>William</hi> for having a very few Foreigners in a great Army in times of War, and this after they are gone out of the Nation, and can do us no harm. It was no Crime in King <hi>James</hi> to ſet up a barbarous Court to take away Mens Liberties and Livelihoods without Law or Reaſon; and yet it is very criminal in this King to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don one of the Members of it upon his Repentance: yea he ſeems angry he doth not hang all K. <hi>James</hi> his Evil-Miniſters, among which probably he had come in for his ſhare. K. <hi>James</hi> in times of Peace executed many by Martial Law, for deſerting, before any Law enabled him ſo to do. And if K. <hi>William</hi> have uſed this Method in time of War, it is very juſtifiable. Yet this is brought in to excuſe that violent invading of the Properties of the richeſt College in <hi>England,</hi> without any Colour of Law, only becauſe the Fellows of it were by their Oaths obliged to deny an unreaſonable Requeſt of the King's. A dreadful Precedent to all the Nation, that their Eſtates were all at the Mercy of that Arbitrary Prince! But the Water runs very low with him, when his utmoſt Malice againſt K. <hi>William</hi> can find nothing to accuſe him for but what was anſwered before; and when he can meet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this Nation blame-worthy, but is forced to run as far as <hi>New-Englaud</hi> for a trifling Complaint.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56682:18"/>
He goes ſo oft into <hi>Scotland</hi> for Inſtances of the King's Arbitrary and Illegal way of Government;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 32.</note> that this, together with the whole Thread of his Stile, made me conclude him to belong to that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We who feel the Juſtice and Gentleneſs of the Government, cannot be eaſily led to think that Matters are managed otherwiſe elſewhere. We find, it's true, the Soldiers are apt upon many occaſions to be irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; but we ſee that upon Complaints, Redreſs is given, and care is taken for the future: And of this the Nation is ſo ſenſible, that Men are willing to paſs over ſeveral things, which otherwiſe could not be well digeſted, and could not at all be born with, if we were not ſure that the Government did not encourage them. For after all, Soldiers are no Philoſophers. Yet this in general did not ſatisfie me: So I writ to a Friend that is nearer the Scene, and knows matters better, and I will give you this account which I had from him. The Author of this Pamphlet is ſo nearly related to Sir <hi>Ja. Man—ry.</hi> that when the Character of the one is given, the other will be beſt known by it. He was of a Presbyterian Education, and entred into ſome Confidences with K. <hi>James</hi>'s Miniſters. But upon this Revolution he got to be a Member of the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in which he bare great Sway, and was a main Stickler for the Abdication, and their preſent Majeſties: He was a conſtant Haranguer during that whole Debate; which he did not manage as ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did. Upon the Extremity to which K. <hi>James</hi> had driven Matters, and the Warrant that extraordinary Occaſions gives for extraordinary Proceedings, he went wholly upon Republican Principles, and ſhe wed ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Fury againſt all the Epiſcopal Party, that his being like to pretend to a great Poſt, upon the Merit of thoſe Services, gave them very ſad Apprehenſions: This was ſignified by many of them to the King:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56682:19"/>For it was he that ſtood upon the taking away of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, and carried it to be made a main Article of their claim of Right; tho it ſtanding then eſtabliſhed by Law, many who agreed to place it among the Grievances that were to be redreſs'd, could not think it reaſonable to claim it as a Right. Since there was then no Law in force for it, and a great many againſt it. He was one of the Three that were ſent up with the Tender of the Crown of <hi>Scotland</hi> to Their Majeſties. But when he ſound that the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to try him firſt in a lower Poſt of the Miniſtry, before he would raiſe him up ſo high as his Ambition carried him: He upon this began to cabal againſt the Government; and upon his return to <hi>Scotland,</hi> he ſowed ſuch Jealouſies and ill Impreſſions of the King, in ſome Peoples Minds, that Matters could not go on; but all things were at a ſtand for above a year, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Dangers of that time. But not content with this, he came back to <hi>London</hi> the following Winter, on pretence indeed to juſtifie himſelf; but in truth to enter into a Treaty with K. <hi>James.</hi> He reſolved to be a Secretary of State; and it was indifferent to him who ſhould be King, provided he might govern. He began his Negotiation under <hi>Nevill Pain</hi>'s Conduct, and drew in a great many with him to enter into a Treaty with K. <hi>James;</hi> the main Point to be carried, was to make ſure of the Plurality of Voices in the Parliament. So the <hi>Jacobites</hi> were applied to, to take the Oaths, and qualifie themſelves, that by ſwearing to this Government, they might betray and over-turn it. Many were perſwaded to this unexampled piece of Treachery; and Sir <hi>Ja.</hi> was very induſtrious in it. A Foreign Force was likewiſe to come from <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> But this was happily diſcovered; ſome that were in the Plot diſliked the Anſwers that they had from K. <hi>James,</hi> then in <hi>Ireland</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> at <hi>St. Germans:</hi> The breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56682:19"/>the Pr. of <hi>Wales</hi> in the Proteſtant Religion was flatly refuſed; and no Security was offered for the Proteſtant Religion; even the Diſpenſing Power was not parted with, only promiſed that Presbytery ſhould be continued in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and Money was ſent over, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with large Promiſes to all the Plotters, in which Sir <hi>Ja.</hi> had the beſt Share: Yet the whole Buſineſs was by that watchful Providence that has never yet fail'd this Government in its greateſt Straits, both diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſcovered: Moſt of thoſe who were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have confeſſed their ſhare in it, and have ſued out their Pardons. When this was firſt diſcovered, Sir <hi>Ja. M.</hi> denyed his knowledge of it in a Strain of the deepeſt Imprecations that could be invented; yet afterwards he confeſſed all, and was favourably recommended to the Queen for her Pardon in Summer 90. But when he found he could not have it unleſs he would frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover all he knew, he kept himſelf out of the way, and has abſconded ever ſince: But being a Man of a virulent Temper, and noted from a Child for a peculiar Talent of Impudence, he has now given us a very full Eſſay of his Abilities that way: And tho ſuch as knew his Notions and Stile, were not long to ſeek in their Conjectures for the Author of ſo black a Libel; yet I am confirmed in this, by the knowledge I have of the Evidence already given in this Matter. This is the Account that is ſent me by one that I have no reaſon to diſtruſt, and who gives me leave to publiſh the Advertiſement he has ſent me. I had ſent away the other parts of this Diſcourſe before I received this, which fills up a Blank that I had made, and in which I muſt retract every part that contradicts this: on which my Reader may ſoon be ſatisfied how far he can rely. Such Men, and ſuch Practices are fit to be employed for bringing us again under the Tyranny from which God has ſo graciouſly delivered us. It is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56682:20"/>no wonder if thoſe who went in the late Revolution without any regard either to the Intereſt of Religion, or of their Country, but only to raiſe their own Fortunes, ſhould prove falſe to it, when they do not find their own account in it: And impotent Rage muſt alwaies ſupport it ſelf by Calumny, for let him ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to perſwade this Nation, that they are fallen under a Tyrannical Government as much as he will, he can never hope to ſucceed in it, as long as they do plainly ſee that it is not ſo: And as long as the <hi>Dutch</hi> Troops are kept under ſo good Diſcipline, and are ſo inoffenſive in their Quarters; none of the Strains of his falſe Rhetorick will be able to raiſe a Spirit in the Nation againſt them.</p>
            <p>As little Succeſs will all he ſays have to perſwade us of the poverty of the Nation, as long as we feel our ſelves in ſo full a Plenty; while our Enemies are reduced to the laſt extremities.</p>
            <p>But one Particular he mentions, did, I confeſs, raiſe my curioſity a little: He ſays the Government order'd a Military Execution of all the Males in <hi>Glencou,</hi> which was executed upon them without any legal Tryal, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Record. This had ſo ſtrange an appearance, and was ſo unlike all the other parts of the King's Government, that has been often taxed with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Clemency, but never till now of Cruelty, that I was in ſome pain, till I had learned what truth there was in it. And in this I have received ſuch full ſatisfaction that I deſire the Reader will by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, conſider how far our Author is to be depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all the reſt. It is well known that there was a Rebellion kept up in the High-lands of <hi>Scotland</hi> long after the reſt of the Country was quiet, and tho' it had been an eaſy thing to have reduced them to the utmoſt extremity, if cruelty had been the King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination; yet he ſent a Perſon of Honour and Credit among them, with a conſiderable Sum to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56682:20"/>as the moſt powerful Argument to work upon them. A Negotiation was ſet on foot, and they all agreed by ſuch a day to lay down their Arms, and take the Oaths: Yet many of them not keeping to this Capitulation, but continuing in Arms ſtill, the day was prolonged twice or thrice. In concluſion, the King ordered them to be held to their Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gave private directions, that if any Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were to be made of ſuch as ſtill ſtood out, it ſhould be of ſuch as had been eminently guilty of Robberies and Murders. A milder and juſter Order was never given. This was executed upon none but known Robbers and Murderers, and ſuch as were ſtill in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Rebellion. If the Officers who executed it did it with too much fierceneſs and Violence, tho' ſuch things are but too natural to Military Men, yet the King has expreſſed a high diſpleaſure at it; and now by this Sample, the Reader may, judge of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Having exerted his utmoſt Malice in miſrepreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing K. <hi>William</hi>'s Actions at home,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 37.</note> his Envy hurries him on to attempt to hide his Glories abroad, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath ſlandered his Conduct in Civil Affairs, he deſpiſes his Martial Proweſs; whereas all <hi>Europe</hi> ſees he hath raiſed the honour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (buried in the Effeminacy and Vices of the two laſt Reigns) to the greateſt Height: And the Great <hi>Lewis</hi> is ſo ſenſible of his Valour, and his Souldiers Courage, that his famed, numerous and diſciplined Troops (as the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet calls them) durſt never attack us, but are bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their very Camps, and tamely ſuffer it, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Shield a better Weapon than a Sword, and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Cowardice of avoiding a Battle, to be the beſt way of making their Campaigns. The <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Laurels,</hi> as our <hi>Author</hi> juſtly ſays, are drench'd in the Tears of his Subjects; for he hath ruined the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56682:21"/>Liberty and Property of his People, to maintain an Army for robbing, burning, and deſtroying all about him. And tis not our King (who only defends the Oppreſſed) but he, that makes all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> pay ſo dear for ſafety and Protection. In <hi>Ireland</hi> our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Prince</hi> hath utterly routed not the <hi>Iriſh</hi> only, but great numbers of well diſciplined and armed <hi>French;</hi> and in little more than two years intirely conquered that large Country: And that which <hi>Spain</hi> yet retains in <hi>Flanders,</hi> is principally owing to K. <hi>William</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and to the Bravery of his Army, who hath at the ſame inſtant dared the <hi>French</hi> by Land, and given them ſuch a Blow at Sea, as they will not recover of many years: A <hi>Victory</hi> that eclipſes the little Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that their <hi>Fleet</hi> had at <hi>Beachy,</hi> and hath done us more good, and them more damage, than the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Land <hi>Battle</hi> could have done; nor will the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Namur</hi> pay for their loſs of ſo many Capital Ships, ſo neceſſary for their Defence by Sea, which is their weak ſide. But it is not enough to ſatiate our Author's ſpite, to trample on the glorious <hi>Reputation</hi> of our King, he reviles all Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> that are in the <hi>Confederacy,</hi> and he will not allow it to be the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> of <hi>France</hi> that ingages them againſt their <hi>Common Oppreſſor,</hi> but imputes it to their particular intereſts. Tho' any unbyaſſed Man, any but a <hi>Loyaliſt</hi> or a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> would ſee, it muſt be univerſal <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and horrid <hi>Barbarities</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>French</hi> on every ſide, that forces the moſt zealous Princes of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> to joyn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a King pretending to the ſame <hi>Religion,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into League with thoſe they count <hi>Hereticks,</hi> to ſave their ſeveral Countries out of the Hand of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Power: Yea the beſt Pope that <hi>Rome</hi> hath had for many years was in the <hi>Confederacy,</hi> not to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Rights and Religion (as this Writer weakly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56682:21"/>ſuggeſts) but to defend his own Privileges againſt a <hi>Prince</hi> that perſecuted the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> both at once, and thereby ſhewed he had no <hi>Religion</hi> at all.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it any wonder that the Confederates loved and truſted the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> more than King <hi>James,</hi> for he had always been true to the Intereſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> and gloriouſly oppoſed the <hi>French</hi> Incroachments, while the late King abetted the <hi>Monſieur</hi> in oppreſſing his own Subjects, and robbing all his Neighbours, and had as little regard to the ſafety of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as to the welfare of <hi>England,</hi> in hopes by this infamous Obſequiouſneſs to be aſſiſted in his pious deſign of Enſlaving and Dragooning his own People; and on this deſirable Work he laviſhed out all thoſe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he had laid up while he was Duke of <hi>York,</hi> which ſo generally diſguſted his Subjects, that no Parliament of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants would ever have given him any more. So that he forfeited his Credit and Intereſt every where but in <hi>France,</hi> and therefore could never be invited into this <hi>Confederacy;</hi> into which, not Ambition, but the love of Juſtice, and his pity to Oppreſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions drew this brave <hi>Prince,</hi> who in the former part of this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> is repreſented to be ſo cunning as to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jole his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> make a meer Tool of his <hi>Father-in-Law,</hi> and to out wit all the Prieſts and Jeſuits: Yet now this ſame King <hi>William</hi> is ſo extream ſilly, that he would make us believe all the Confederates make a <hi>Fool</hi> of him, and tho' he owns he knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the private Agreements King <hi>William</hi> hath made with the Confederates, yet he confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces, We are to have all the <hi>Loſs</hi> and they all the <hi>Gain</hi> by this <hi>League;</hi> and upon this Subject he rails blindfold till he be out of Breath; but all that have Eyes in their Heads will ſee through this winking Malice, and ſooner believe that he is a ſhameleſs Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniator, than that all the <hi>Confederate Princes</hi> are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56682:22"/>Knaves, and King <hi>William</hi> a meer Stepping ſtone to their Deſigns, as this modeſt Gentleman upon bare Conjecture repreſents them.</p>
            <p>With the like random Gueſſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 39.</note> he goes on to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter us with idle Suggeſtions, That we are like to have no Advantage by a Succeſsful War in this <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy,</hi> and dreadful Loſſes if it prove unfortunate in the Iſſue: To which I ſhall only reply, That King <hi>William</hi> is as eminent for his <hi>Prudence</hi> as for his <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> and the Nation is convinced they may truſt him with making War and Peace for them, ſince his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and theirs are one and the ſame. The <hi>Dutch</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> do not aim at, or intend the Deſtruction of <hi>France,</hi> as the <hi>French</hi> King doth at theirs; but only at the humbling and reducing him to his juſt Bounds, and to ſecure themſelves againſt his <hi>Ravages</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations.</hi> So that he is ridiculous in talking of the Confederates falling out who ſhall have the Power at Sea, and who the Provinces at Land, when that <hi>Great Empire</hi> falls to be divided amongſt them. The Confederates glory in the Juſtice of their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which is to recover the late <hi>Encroachments</hi> from <hi>France,</hi> and defend their preſent Poſſeſſions from Burning and Deſtruction; and they hope the Righteous <hi>God</hi> will make their <hi>Cauſe</hi> as proſperous as it is Juſt and Neceſſary: and if it prove ſo, every one of the Confederates will be content with his Share in the Common Safety. But if for our Sins it ſhould prove Unfortunate, we are as likely and as able, under the Conduct of our Wiſe and Valiant King to defend and ſecure our ſelves, as any Nation or Country in this <hi>Confederacy.</hi> Nor will his Eloquence in ſetting off the Miſeries of our falling into the <hi>French</hi> Mercy, have any other Effect upon this brave Nation, than to make them more obſtinate in fighting againſt, and more wary in treating with ſo bloody and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Foe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:56682:22"/>
But the Perfection of his Politicks,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 40.</note> is ſhewed in his learned <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> That all Chriſtian Princes wiſh the dethroning of King <hi>William,</hi> and the reſtoring of K. <hi>James,</hi> imitating <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Tool, who being blind, fanſied all the Houſe was dark. That <hi>France</hi> will endeavour both, as well by Force as Treadhery, that Unchriſtian King hath ſufficiently ſhewed, to put us upon our Guard. But the Houſe of <hi>Austria</hi> cannot have a more Faithful and Powerful Ally on the <hi>Engliſh Throne</hi> than King <hi>William,</hi> who will certainly aſſiſt them to bring King <hi>Lewis</hi> to Reaſon, and be their beſt <hi>Guarrantee</hi> when he is reduced to a Juſt Peace. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as K. <hi>James</hi>'s former Carriage hath convinced them, That if he had Power it would always be at the <hi>French</hi> King's Service Right or Wrong. Again, if the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (as he pretends) hated King <hi>William,</hi> they muſt keep him on the <hi>Throne,</hi> to prevent his return among them. But their Affection and intire Confidence in him is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by the great <hi>Command</hi> they now give him; which ſhews they believe the greater his Power is, the ſafer are their Liberties; and they know, K. <hi>James</hi> mortally hates them, and never can forgive them. His Fancy that <hi>Sweden</hi> ſhould wiſh for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King and his Heir, both of that odious <hi>Religion</hi> which they have baniſhed out of their <hi>Country</hi> with their lawful <hi>Queen</hi> who had embraced it, is as peculiar and ridiculous, as that <hi>Denmark</hi> (which lends us For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) ſhould hate King <hi>William</hi> for bringing one of their Blood Royal to ſo near a Poſſibility of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown. And <hi>England</hi> knows it is her Intereſt to have a King that will protect them from the fatal Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of <hi>France,</hi> ſo that all his Politicks fail him; and he muſt ſuppoſe us all, as he did (<hi>Pag.</hi> 2.) to be <hi>Ideots</hi> and Madmen, to be enticed into a Civil War with ſuch <hi>Paltry Reaſonings</hi> as theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56682:23"/>
His laſt Exploit is to deſpiſe his Adverſary, and charge him again with Impudence and Emptineſs, for wondring any Man ſhould be ſo weak, as to believe that K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reſtauration is the way to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion and here with his uſual Confidence he undertakes to prove and anſwer all things; but of his Performance let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 41.</note> he will prove our Religion was in no danger of being over-turned by King <hi>James</hi>'s Practices. And here again all <hi>that</hi> Prince's open trampling on Law and Right, all his Zeal by Promiſes and Threats to make <hi>Converts,</hi> his Swarms of Prieſts, his ſtanding <hi>Army</hi> to protect them, his <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Rigour</hi> againſt all that oppoſe his illegal Methods to bring <hi>Popery</hi> to be the eſtabliſhed <hi>Religion,</hi> are by this Jeſuit in Diſguiſe, ſmoothed over, or paſt by, as nothing extraordinary, nothing but a deſire natural to Mankind to procure ſome eaſe to them of their own Perſwaſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if this were all, why did he not accept of that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which his Loyal <hi>Proteſtant Parliament</hi> offered to grant, that is <hi>Indulgence</hi> as to their Worſhip to all <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and Liberty to preferr a certain number of others? This he rejected with <hi>Rage,</hi> and diſſolved that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only becauſe this would not anſwer his deſign of putting all Power into Popiſh Hands. And as to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience the thing needs none of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: The <hi>Roman</hi> Faith indeed needs ſeverity; without which no Nation under Heaven would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it. But our moſt Holy <hi>Faith</hi> can ſubſiſt without Compulſion; and therefore this Nation was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, if a further deſign had not been diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. We were ſure K. <hi>James</hi> could not love Liberty of Conſcience for its own ſake; firſt, becauſe Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abſolutely damns all other Religions: And can a devout Papiſt give whole Nations leave to go to Hell? Secondly, becauſe it neither is nor ever was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56682:23"/>allowed in any Popiſh Country where that Church had Power to perſecute. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> becauſe he uſed all means but open Force (which he durſt not practiſe) to urge Men not half convinc'd, to declare themſelves <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt their Conſcience, as divers of them now declare: <hi>Wherefore</hi> Liberty of Conſcience was known to be inconſiſtent with the Principles and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of his Church, and contrary to his <hi>French</hi> Maſter's Copy as well as to his own Judgment; and all this makes it plain he only pretended to love Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience to break the Church of <hi>England,</hi> divide <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Popery</hi> at the laſt: So that the thing it ſelf was as dangerous in his Hands, as the Methods were unjuſtifiable: The Counſel was given by <hi>Contzen</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> long ſince, That to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by ſeemingly favouring all Parties, was the ready way to bring in (as our <hi>Author</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls it) the <hi>Roman Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt it ſeems it is with him but a bare Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſome did intend by <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag</hi> 42.</note> to preferr <hi>Catholicks</hi> and propagate that Religion, yet he thinks K. <hi>James</hi> underſtood the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>England</hi> ſo well, that he would never attempt it. It s now his <hi>Cue</hi> to make K. <hi>James</hi> very wiſe, even in a Point where his zeal blinded him, whereas juſt before he was the weakeſt Man alive, and foreſaw nothing; and tho' he uſed the means, this ſelf contradicting Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will not allow he wiſhed for the <hi>End:</hi> I am ſure no body was in ſo much <hi>Grace</hi> with him as theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> and new <hi>Converts,</hi> whoſe warm <hi>Brain,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizing <hi>Faith</hi> intirely guided him: And it is no thanks to K. <hi>James</hi> his or their good <hi>Intentions,</hi> that theſe <hi>Projects</hi> did not ſucceed, but to the early diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>Plot,</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi>'s brave oppoſing him in bringing it to effect. But <hi>Truth</hi> will out, and therefore, finally, he grants (that which all <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56682:24"/>knows to have been plain Matter of Fact) that K. <hi>James</hi> did every thing to advance <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſuppreſs the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and then he guards himſelf with the little Progreſs that was made— Which is falſe; for in leſs than two years time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he pulled off his <hi>Mask,</hi> there were many in the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Camp,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, Inns of Court;</hi> in all <hi>Cities</hi> and in the <hi>Country,</hi> who really or feignedly turned. Thouſands more complyed, and were ready to ſhake Hands with their <hi>Religion</hi> as ſoon as their Intereſt told them they might do it ſafely. And what might have been the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of our <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> (as ſome expound it) in a year or two longer is eaſy to judge: But he would recall his grant again, and ſays, If the late King had by real Diſcoveries evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced his <hi>Intentions</hi> to ruine the eſtabliſhed <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> nothing but an univerſal <hi>Defection</hi> could have followed. <hi>Oportet Mendacem eſſe Memorem:</hi> He ſaid Pag. 6th. That the <hi>Army</hi> was quite Poyſoned, and that there was nothing ſound and untainted in the whole Kingdom: and Pag. 11th. There was an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Defection of his Children, Servants, Souldiers and Subjects. Therefore by his own <hi>Rule</hi> K. <hi>James</hi> had made real, publick, and undoubted Diſcoveries of his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> to ruine the eſtabliſhed <hi>Religion.</hi> Well, but he urges, That the <hi>Catholicks</hi> were but few — How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they daily encreaſed, and had a Biggotted King to protect them from fear of <hi>Laws,</hi> an <hi>Army</hi> (after the deſigned <hi>Regulation</hi>) ready to defend them, the <hi>Sectaries</hi> generally on their ſide, and wanted nothing but a pre-engaged Parliament to make them upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. As to the Laws, upon which he makes ſo large an <hi>Encomium,</hi> as if they were a ſufficient ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to our <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I grant they would have been ſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 43.</note> if our King, knowing this, had not reſolved to break through all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56682:24"/>theſe <hi>Fences,</hi> and pick'd out Judges for his purpoſe, who expounded the Laws as the King directed, and ſet up his Diſpenſing Power at one blow to null them all. <hi>Laws</hi> are, 'tis true (as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaith) the Soul of a City, but the Magiſtrate is the Soul of the Laws; which are a dead Rule, a meer Shadow, when the Prince and his Judges conſpire not to execute them, and no Man dare claim the Benefit, or need fear the Penalty of them. What good did the Laws do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Proteſtant</hi> cited before the <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court?</hi> What hurt did they do to any illegal Officers, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, or promoted Prieſts? What Security were they to <hi>Corporations</hi> when <hi>Jeofferies</hi> roared out the King's Will. Old <hi>Maynard,</hi> when King <hi>William</hi> told him he had out-lived moſt of his Profeſſion, truly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, That if He had not come over he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-lived the Law it ſelf. And we had ſeen the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant in one part of his Reign ſubvert all the Laws of his Country, and deſtroy all the Liberties of his Subjects, — He was going on in the ſame Deſign, <hi>Licet non paſſibus aequis:</hi> And why ſhould not he hope and we fear, that what was done at our next Door was poffible to be done here. 'Tis true, the Nation was in as little danger of loving him then, as they are now of wiſhing his Return: But thoſe Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies (which he rails at in the laſt Page, and here commends) had ſignified nothing if he had gone a little further in theſe Methods. He reſolved to have no Parliament, but ſuch an one as would engage before hand to betray their Country, and comply with him in every thing? And was it likely an oppreſſed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could manage a wiſe and diſcreet Treaty with ſuch a <hi>King,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Parliament?</hi> He foreſees it will be objected, That K. <hi>James</hi> being a Friend and Ally of <hi>France,</hi> could not want <hi>French</hi> Forces to compel the more obſtinate ſort of <hi>Hereticks;</hi> which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56682:25"/>is a dreadful, but a certain truth; and he gives no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction by his Sham-Reaſons to the contrary: Firſt, K. <hi>James</hi> (he thinks) was not ſo loſt to all Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Morality to accept <hi>French</hi> Troops; for now you muſt know he is to be repreſented very Diſcreet; and he that was ſo eaſily drawn in by his Enemies to act againſt his Judgment, is now ſo wiſe and wary, that for fear of ill Conſequences, he will not admit any Succors from his Friends to help him to ſave a Million of Souls, <hi>Credat Judaeus Apella.</hi> He that was training up many of the old Race of murdering <hi>Iriſh</hi> for this meritorious Work, would not (if occaſion had been) have ſcrupled adding <hi>French Dragoons.</hi> And our Authors <hi>Morality</hi> is not to be relyed on, when he ſaith, K. <hi>James</hi> refuſed <hi>French</hi> Succours at the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for 'tis well known the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Hands were full elſewhere, he having then made a violent and treacherous Invaſion upon the Empire, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Philipsburg:</hi> For his Intelligence from <hi>England</hi> was that he relyed on, he believed that this Kingdom was falling into a Diviſion and a Civil War, that would be ſo equal and laſt ſo long, that he might fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Conqueſts in <hi>Germany,</hi> and yet come time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to compleat our Ruin, while we ſhould have been deſtroying one another. Otherwiſe K. <hi>James</hi> (if he had not wanted time, and his <hi>Ally-Forces</hi> ready) would no more have refuſed <hi>French Troops</hi> to keep the Prince from coming in, than he now ſcruples to uſe them for turning him out.</p>
            <p>But he pretends it was not the <hi>French</hi> King's Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to lend K.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>James</hi> any Forces to aſſiſt him in the Converſion of <hi>England.</hi> But ſuppoſe he were bent upon it, and would hazard three Crowns on Earth for it (as his ſaying was) and chanced to be oppoſed in it by his ſtubborn Subjects, K. <hi>Lewis</hi> muſt not let his dear Friend ſink or ſuffer by following his <hi>Example,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56682:25"/>eſpecially ſince he was ſure as long as this King was in Power, he could not want one that would ſtand by him in all his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Reſerve:</hi> And I dare affirm the greateſt part of the <hi>Nation</hi> firmly believes, That within a little time, King <hi>Lewis</hi> would have ſent, and King <hi>James</hi> have accepted a Body of booted <hi>French Apoſtles</hi> for this religious Work. To divert with rational Fear, our <hi>Author</hi> ſtarts an improbable <hi>Paradox,</hi> and for three Columns together purſues it with full cry, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>French</hi> K. rather wiſhes <hi>England</hi> ſhould remain <hi>Proteſtant</hi> than become <hi>Papiſt,</hi> becauſe (forſooth) he is in no danger of an <hi>Invaſion</hi> while the Nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be of different Religions: Which frivolous and falſe reaſoning deſerves no Anſwer; ſo that I will make a few brief Remarks upon it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 45.</note> he hath learned of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> to ſuppoſe <hi>England</hi> was always terrible to <hi>France</hi> till Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi>'s Reign, and to blame the <hi>Reformation</hi> for this: <hi>Whereas</hi> it is well known that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> loſt their hold in <hi>France</hi> in the Reigns of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6th. and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> two <hi>Popiſh Princes;</hi> and none of our Kings were ever more courted by <hi>France</hi> than that Illuſtrious reformed Queen, who broke the dangerous growth of the moſt <hi>Catholick King,</hi> tho' her Subjects and his were of different Religions. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly ſuppoſes all the <hi>French</hi> are zealous <hi>Catholicks,</hi> whereas thoſe of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> there (the Clergy excepted) are no <hi>Bigots;</hi> and there are many thouſands who have by Cruelty been forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare for <hi>Popery,</hi> that yet are <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in their Hearts, and the <hi>French</hi> King knows that if he be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by a <hi>Proteſtant Prince,</hi> theſe Men will endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him by a <hi>Revoſt. Thirdly,</hi> we obſerve that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Catholick</hi> Countries have been ſo Barbarouſly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56682:26"/>and their <hi>Princes</hi> ſo injured by the <hi>French</hi> K. that (without any regard to his Profeſſion) He who ſhall be the happy Inſtrument to humble <hi>France,</hi> will be gratefull to the greateſt part of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Mounſieur</hi> uſurps upon <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I muſt obſerve that the <hi>French</hi> King's late inhumane Uſage of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> hath made him odious, eſpecially, to all reformed <hi>Nations;</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> have lately ſhewed they will and can fight as bravely againſt <hi>France</hi> as ever their da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Anceſtors have done: Wherefore all this <hi>Banter</hi> of the <hi>Author</hi>'s is a falſe <hi>Alarm,</hi> deſigned to make us ſecure on that ſide where our danger is.</p>
            <p>To this he adds another <hi>Fiction</hi> of K. <hi>James</hi> his offering us to carve out our own <hi>Securities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 26.</note> and dreams of laſting, legal, full and happy <hi>Settlements</hi> we might have had under him: But when, and to whom were theſe Offers made? the <hi>Prince</hi> made Offers to him, and deſired a <hi>Parliament</hi> might be called, but K. <hi>James</hi> burnt the Writs, and fled from the Treaty, dreading nothing more than a <hi>Legal Settlement</hi> to tie up his Hands. Promiſes he had made many, eſpecially in his <hi>Diſtreſs;</hi> but alas, he had taught us they were Inſignificant; and it was plain enough the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> were always his <hi>Darlings:</hi> For the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, he never loved, them, yea, his parting Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhews his Hopes, <hi>viz.</hi> That we ſhould be ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, as to ſend for him again upon his own Terms: He therefore that would not ſtay to redreſs any thing, nor endure either a <hi>Treaty</hi> or a <hi>Parliament,</hi> for fear of being bound to ſecure us by <hi>Law,</hi> and now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to break in upon us by <hi>Force.</hi> He is to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for all the Money and Lives ſpent in our own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Defence.</hi> We deſired to be quiet under him, and neither began nor continue this <hi>War,</hi> further than for the ſafety of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56682:26"/>he reſolved not to ſecure: So that as the <hi>Crocodile</hi> weeps over them it intends to devour, this <hi>Hypocrite</hi> ſheds his deceitful tears over bleeding <hi>England,</hi> which he and his Party have forced into a War, and now would wheedle us into a Peace more fatal than all the other Miſchiefs they have involv'd us in.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe he would perſwade us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 47.</note> that this is a religious <hi>War,</hi> and notes, <q>That Defections on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> generally terminate in the deſtruction of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the pretenders to it:</q> Where obſerve that he cannot find any ſuch things in <hi>Defections</hi> for <hi>Popery:</hi> They doubtleſs in his Opinion are lawful and proſperous: He never heard of the <hi>League</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> nor of the Earl of <hi>Weſtmorland</hi>'s <hi>Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> from Queen <hi>Elizabeth, &amp;c. Papiſts</hi> may do this, but <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are only to ſit ſtill and have their <hi>Throats</hi> cut. We thank him for ſo plainly telling us what ſide he is of. But to paſs that by, his <hi>Examples</hi> ſhew he underſtands foreign Hiſtory no better than our <hi>Chronicles. Ziſca</hi>'s <hi>Bohemian</hi> War was begun for both <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties, Anno</hi> 1419. And beſides the Succeſs in the beginning, it had this <hi>Event,</hi> That the Religion they defended was profeſſed there for about 200 years after, and (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> notes) tho' War and Perſecution both have been uſed, yet this Doctrine could never be routed out. <hi>Coſmog.</hi> C. 2. Pag. 78. The Civil Wars in <hi>Germany</hi> were defenſive againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, who hoped (as our late King alſo did) to extirpate the <hi>Northern Hereſie.</hi> But the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> was the ſetling the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> in many Countries and Cities where it remains to this day; and the Imperial Family wears greater Scars of it than any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes concerned in it. 'Tis true, the ſecond <hi>Bohemian</hi> War had an unfortunate Iſſue, by the neglect of timely <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Succours; but there the <hi>Papiſts</hi> drove out the rightful King, and yet
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56682:27"/>proſpered: So that this Inſtance ſhould have been brought to prove that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not the only People that fight againſt their Princes to ſettle their own <hi>Religion,</hi> or ſet up Kings that will defend it. The <hi>Hungarian</hi> War on the <hi>Protestants</hi> Part, was purely in defence of their Liberties, and to guard themſelves from an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal and cruel Perſecution, of which (as he intimates, <hi>Pag.</hi> 37.) the <hi>Emperor</hi> was the <hi>Author,</hi> and they were ready to have laid down their Arms if they could have had any reaſonable <hi>Conditions;</hi> and the <hi>Emperor</hi> hath got nothing by that War; nor hath he ſo extinguiſhed <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> there, but that he muſt grant the free Exerciſe of it, or he will never have Peace on that ſide.</p>
            <p>However, 'tis well he grants at laſt that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may be Victorious ſo long as they only <hi>Petition,</hi> tho' with <hi>Arms</hi> in their Hands: For this was our caſe ſo long as our King would ſtay to be <hi>Petitioned.</hi> Theſe are all the diſcouraging <hi>Instances</hi> he can pick up, but he might have found as many to encourage us if he had pleaſed. <hi>Holland, Scotland, Geneva,</hi> ſome of the <hi>Cantons,</hi> and divers <hi>Hans-Towns</hi> were fortunate in their <hi>Defections</hi> to keep off <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery;</hi> ſo that one or two Inſtances on the other ſide do not make the Scales even, only we may juſtly wonder to hear a <hi>Jacobite</hi> who rails at Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reaſoning, <hi>Pag.</hi> 57. preſſing an Argument from Succeſs, and muſt admoniſh this <hi>Author</hi> to look into the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Papers, <hi>Pag.</hi> 16, 17. where he will find that which way ſoever the ſucceſs go, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> the firſt, King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, and their Parliaments; yea, and Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> himſelf have declared the thing law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and reſolved, That where Princes broke in upon their Subjects <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> they ought to defend thenſelves, and might juſtly be aſſiſted in ſuch a War.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:56682:27"/>
Wherefore if his <hi>Rhetorick</hi> ſhould move ſome weak People,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 48.</note> his <hi>Logick</hi> cannot work upon any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man, who concludes from two <hi>Examples</hi> neither proper nor truly related, that this and all <hi>Wars</hi> wherein <hi>Proteſtants</hi> defend their <hi>Religion</hi> muſt be unfortunate: But how ſhould he be a <hi>Prophet</hi> to foretel the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of <hi>Wars,</hi> who is ſo ignorant as to miſtake the preſent <hi>Emperour</hi>'s Name, whom he calls <hi>Rodolph</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Leopold,</hi> like the ridiculous <hi>Star-Gazer</hi> who was predicting future <hi>Events</hi> by looking up to the <hi>Stars,</hi> and dropt into a deep Pit juſt before him. And it ſeems at laſt his Heart fails too as to the certainty of our defenſive <hi>Wars</hi> ending unfortunately; ſo that he turns his Threats into Wheedle, and would have us tamely to ſend for the late King again, and accept of his <hi>Conceſſions,</hi> (which we never yet ſaw) yea to tell he may return upon a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Foot. But I muſt tell him, we can make no ſuch Offers now, without out King and Parliament; and if we could, whatever promiſes he ſhould make to get us once more into his Power, he would certainly break them, unleſs he would return with a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Heart, which is never to be hoped for. He concludes with that which he calls anſwering the <hi>Objections</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt King <hi>James</hi> his Return, but indeed with nauſeous Repetitions of that which he had ſaid over and over before, ſo that I may Anſwer all that is new in theſe Pages in a little Room. <hi>First,</hi> we ſay he cannot return but by a <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> and he thinks he muſt and ought to be allowed 15000 <hi>French</hi> for his ordinary Guard, and theſe he hopes, with the acceſſion of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> who will deſert King <hi>William,</hi> will do the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> Alas, he forgets that moſt of thoſe who will fly to a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prince, at the Head of a <hi>French Popiſh Army,</hi> muſt be <hi>Papists,</hi> or very looſe Principled <hi>Protestants.</hi> The main body of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56682:28"/>
               <hi>Nation,</hi> the <hi>Nobility, Gentry</hi> and <hi>People</hi> are averſe to K. <hi>James,</hi> who uſed them rudely and left them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Care of them; and they will freely venture their Lives for King <hi>William,</hi> a Prince of their own <hi>Religion,</hi> who reſcued them once from extream Danger, and hath ventured his Life for their ſafety ever ſince: He forgets alſo what he ſaid, <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. That <hi>Catholicks</hi> will fight to the laſt to eſcape the Dominion of ſuch as they believe <hi>Hereticks:</hi> Now is it not much more ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> will alſo ſight to the laſt againſt ſuch as they know to be not only <hi>Papists</hi> but perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>French</hi> Dragoons and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Murtherers? In ſhort, let K. <hi>James</hi> (if he have ſo great an Intereſt here) ſtay till the <hi>Nation</hi> ſend a <hi>General Embaſſy</hi> to recal him as they did in his Brother's Caſe: Or otherwiſe let not him or his <hi>Friends</hi> hope he can force himſelf upon Us, without ſuch an Oppoſition as muſt end either in his or their Ruine, or the Deſtruction of the beſt part of the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch a <hi>Conquest</hi> would make us <hi>Slaves</hi> both to K. <hi>James</hi> and to the <hi>French</hi> King,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 49.</note> to whom he was ever obſequious; but the merit of reſtoring him will make him his <hi>Vaſſal:</hi> So that we ſhall have <hi>Cham</hi>'s <hi>Fate</hi> to be Servant of Servants; and if K. <hi>Lewis</hi> help to make us ſo, he will account theſe three Crowns a <hi>Purchace</hi> and no <hi>Preſent.</hi> But conſidering how uneaſy <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> muſt be under a double <hi>Slavery,</hi> the only way to tame them muſt be a ſevere <hi>Perſecution;</hi> to which, if Intereſt did not lead the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Ambition</hi> would: For he Dragooned his own Subjects againſt his Intereſt, purely out of <hi>Vain-Glory,</hi> and to ſhew his Will was abſolute and uncontroulable, and that neither <hi>Conſcience</hi> nor the <hi>Fear of God</hi> ſhould exempt any Man from Obedience to it; beſides, we ſaw by K. <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Elight,</hi> that he conſiders not the <hi>Nation</hi>'s ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when he thinks himſelf in Danger, and when he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56682:28"/>hath his truſty <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French Guards</hi> about him; 'tis but pretending our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> are inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with his Security, and then <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> muſt be advanced to keep him in the <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may take the <hi>Author</hi>'s Word for K. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi> to the <hi>Scotch Plotters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 50.</note> (ſince he hath no doubt been in all <hi>Plots</hi> ſince the <hi>Revolution</hi>) but ſuppoſe they have his Word, his Hand and Seal for theſe <hi>Favours,</hi> we know he will promiſe any thing in his Diſtreſs; but were he reſtored and in full Power, it would be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he was under a <hi>Force</hi> when he made theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſo not obliged to perform them. Moreover I would ask why he did not offer ſuch <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> here, while he had Power to call a <hi>Parliament</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them? The only reaſon muſt be, that if his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi> had paſſed into Laws, and other Securities had been given, he could never have ruined the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and ſet up his own <hi>Religion:</hi> Nor would he be ſo free to grant now, if he did not know how to be abſolved from fulfilling thoſe <hi>Grants.</hi> His <hi>Pre-Engagements</hi> to the <hi>Pope</hi> are well known; we have his <hi>Letters</hi> to the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father,</hi> and hear of the <hi>Arguments</hi> uſed at <hi>Rome</hi> for his <hi>Holineſſes</hi>'s Aid, which are his loſing three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> for his <hi>Zeal</hi> to reduce us to the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and his Reſolution upon his <hi>Reſtauration</hi> to promote the ſame pious <hi>VVork.</hi> Oh! but King <hi>VVilliam</hi> (he ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts) hath made more <hi>Engagements</hi> to the <hi>Holy-Chair,</hi> to gain the Pope to favour his <hi>Advancement</hi> to the <hi>Throne.</hi> Very Comical! King <hi>VVilliam</hi>'s <hi>Advancement</hi> to the <hi>Throne</hi> was neither foreſeen by the Pope, nor any <hi>Catholick</hi> Prince, nor by himſelf: Some of them might poſſibly know of his Deſcent, and favour it, as it might tend to weaken their common Enemy the <hi>French</hi> King and his only conſiderable <hi>Allie,</hi> but none of them foreſaw that K. <hi>James</hi> would deſert, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Liberty the <hi>Papiſts</hi> enjoy here is owing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56682:29"/>to King <hi>William</hi>'s good Nature and Tenderneſs, not to any Promiſes he made beforehand to any of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates.</p>
            <p>His next <hi>Attack</hi> is upon Dr. <hi>King</hi>'s Book of the <hi>State</hi> of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 51.</note> which proves that K. <hi>James</hi> expreſſed his <hi>Hatred</hi> of <hi>Protestants,</hi> and his <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotry</hi> for <hi>Popery</hi> there ſince the <hi>Revolution:</hi> A Book writ with that known <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Firmneſs</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that every Page of it is <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> which hath been often threatned with an Anſwer, but the long <hi>Silence</hi> of the party ſhews guilt and deſpair. As for this <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's</hi> Falſhoods and Calumnies, I refer the Reader to that convincing Tract, which not only confutes all our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary's ſham Stories of theſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Affairs, but expoſes his Impudence in venturing his Credit by telling ſuch <hi>Improbabilities.</hi> The <hi>Truth</hi> in ſhort is, that <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> had diſarmed all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> before K. <hi>James</hi> came over, and left them naked to the Outrages of the bloody <hi>Rapperees,</hi> who plundered whole Towns and killed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and upon Complaint, no <hi>Proteſtant</hi> could have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; K. <hi>James</hi> would not employ nor truſt any of them, their cauſes in all <hi>Courts</hi> ſtill went againſt them, the Soldiers oppreſſed them, the meaneſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over them, their Lands were unjuſtly taken from them by that tyrannical Law of <hi>Repealing Settlements,</hi> and this by K. <hi>James</hi>'s own Sollicitation, who ſtruggled with his Biſhops and modeſt Judges to carry it, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was duly informed of the Cruelty and Injuſtice of it, ſtill preſſed it, and at laſt got it paſſed to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of Thouſand <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Families, moſt of which had purchaſed and paid for theſe Eſtates. Thoſe who ſtay'd in <hi>Ireland</hi> were oppreſſed, impriſoned and uſed barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly. Thoſe who fled for ſafety or for Bread, were attainted of High Treaſon, by an Act that never had a Precedent in any Age ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> Proſcriptions. Many thouſands of all Qualities and Ages and of both Sexes were Condemned without Citation or any ſort
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56682:29"/>of Evidence brought againſt them. And whereas to give ſome Colour to ſo Barbarous a proceeding, they had a day aſſigned them to come in, after which the Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was to take place; yet that none of them might be the better, for the Orders were given, and care was taken that no Man ſhould come by the ſight of it. And every where <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches were taken from them by <hi>Force</hi> and given to <hi>Popiſh Priests,</hi> by the <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Connivance</hi> of the late King. Yet all his was done in thoſe parts of <hi>Ireland</hi> where the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> were very peaceable under him. And now let the World judge whether theſe undeniable Matters of Fact be not a ſufficient <hi>Cure</hi> for any <hi>Engliſh Protestants</hi> wiſhing to ſee him reſtored to a Power to do the like Miſchieſs here: His Temper and Principles we ſee are the ſame they were, in the height of his Attempts on our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and if we put him into the ſame <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> we ſhould ſoon feel the Effects of our <hi>Folly</hi> and his <hi>Revenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We agree with him that King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt was ill treated to the great Scandal of that part of the <hi>Nation</hi> who were his Enemies;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 52.</note> but when his Son ſaw how dire Effects a few ſtretches of the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and ſome groundleſs Fears of <hi>Popery</hi> had produced, methinks he ſhould not in the ſame Age have ſet up a more illegal <hi>High-Commiſſion-Court,</hi> nor openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelf a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> and againſt Law and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given all the beſt Places in <hi>England</hi> to thoſe of that Perſwaſion: Nor ſhould he have Impriſoned or Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men contrary to Law, nor committed more Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages by his Army in times of Peace, than have ever ſince been committed by a more numerous Army in time of War. He therefore, not King <hi>William</hi> is moſt concerned in that unhappy <hi>Precedent.</hi> The kind Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which one of his Adverſaries urged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Non-ſwearing <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have an equal ſhare of Logick and Truth; for which cauſe this <hi>Author</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56682:30"/>evades than anſwers them; he brings in over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Grants to the <hi>Scotch</hi> Plotters, which were ſhewed before to be inſignificant, and at laſt paſſes his Word for his Maſter, That he will be very kind to them at his <hi>Return,</hi> and perſwades them to believe all things and doubt nothing; tho' Experience and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon both ſhew there is no ground for them to expect any thing, or rely on any Promiſes: I ſhall therefore only beg of the worthy Gentlemen concerned, to read the Paper cited, and compare thoſe ſolid Reaſons with this Man's ſmooth <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> and then ſhall leave the obſtinate that Cardinal's <hi>Benediction, Si vult Populus decipi decipiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Caution is as prudent as the former was charitable,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 53.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> That we muſt beware leaſt another <hi>Revolution</hi> ſhould ſet up the <hi>Prerogative</hi> higher than is conſiſtent with the Subject's Liberties: For 'tis natural for all Men, eſpecially the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to run from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream to another, and K. <hi>James</hi>'s Inclination and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt will lead him to it: The <hi>Papists</hi> will work upon his Fears, and plead it is neceſſary, and many <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> will joyn with them either to make their Peace or to curry favour. And if <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s <hi>Invaſion</hi> which was ſo eaſily quaſhed and ſoon over, gave colour to raiſe ſo great a ſtanding Army, this laſt <hi>Revolution</hi> may be eaſily improved into keeping up a greater Force, and lodging more power in the King. He proceeds to anſwr ſome Queſtions which that <hi>Author</hi> asks, and firſt owns he thinks not himſelf bound in Conſcience to fight for <hi>Popery</hi> againſt the <hi>Protestant Faith;</hi> but will not allow fighting for the <hi>Restauration</hi> of K. <hi>James</hi> can be called by that name. I anſwer by an old Logical <hi>Maxim, Cauſa Cauſae eſt Cauſa cauſati.</hi> He that fights to put a Prince into Power that will certainly uſe that Power to promote <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſuppreſs the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> and fights to eject another Prince who hath reſcued us from extream Danger
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56682:30"/>Popery, and eſtabliſh the Proteſtant Faith. He fights for the former and againſt the latter Religion. As to his repeated Phraſe of King <hi>James,</hi> his deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon a Proteſtant Foot. I have reaſon to believe he doth not wiſh to be ſo reſtored; for then he muſt leave moſt of his Prieſts behind him, and deliver up his Son to be brought up a Proteſtant, and give Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for it; and that he will by no means like: Yet if he can find a Popiſh Nation ſo tame as to have let in a Proteſtant Head (without ſuch Conditions) upon a Popiſh Foot, we may promiſe him to follow the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. We can ſhew him a Country that obliged a Popiſh Head to quit her Crown, and march off upon a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Foot, <hi>viz. Sweden:</hi> And can inſtance in <hi>France</hi> where <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. King <hi>James</hi>'s Grandfather, ſo long as he was a Proteſtant, was kept out by Papiſts with Force and Arms, and could not be admitted quietly, till he declared himſelf of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> And no People of any Religion (if they can help it) will ſet a King up over them, who is an Enemy to their eſtabliſhed Faith: Wherefore till K. <hi>James</hi> ſincerely becomes of the Engliſh Religion, tho' it ſhould be his Intereſt and Inclination to return, it will not be ours.</p>
            <p>He is alſo very free to declare he will not fight for his Prince againſt the Laws;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 54.</note> but theſe are only words. He will fight for a King who endeavoured to alter the whole Frame of our Government; who challenged, and exerciſed a Power to vacate and ſuſpend what Laws he pleaſed; that reſolves to be above, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law, and will endure no Judge who ſhall not force the Laws already made to bow to his Will. No Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that will not promiſe before-hand to Make and Repeal what Laws he pleaſes. Now if this be not fighting for a Prince againſt the Laws, I know not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56682:31"/>what is. As to his Inſinuation, That King <hi>William</hi> hath broken and intends to deſtroy our Laws: It is as groundleſs, as 'tis malitious; he hath done nothing but by Advice of his <hi>Convention, Parliaments,</hi> and <hi>Judges;</hi> and hath very ſparingly exerciſed his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, even in this time of War, when Neceſſity ſometimes required it: ſo that to fight againſt him, is really to fight againſt the Maintainer and Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our Liberties and Laws, and conſequently of our Religion, whereof theſe Laws are the beſt Fence. And therefore, as he well hints, the French King, who reſolv'd to change his Subjects Faith, firſt made them Slaves, that ſo he might make them Papiſts; and he who copied out that Pattern in <hi>England,</hi> began with our Laws, and pulled up all the Fences; and his next Work would have been to ſuppreſs our Religion; which if it be dear to us, we muſt never expoſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to one that uſed ſuch Methods, but ſtick to him who can never deſign to make us Papiſts, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can never deſire, or need, to make us Slaves.</p>
            <p>But our Author thinks,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 55.</note> whatever Cauſe Proteſtants have, they are the only People of the World, who muſt not enter into a Religious War; no, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves from Popiſh Aggreſſors: As if their Religion alone, ſtripped them of that univerſal natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Right of Self-Defence, and let looſe all Mankind upon them. He hath no Remarks upon the Holy <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> League; none upon his dear Monſieur's League with Infidells. 'Tis only Wicked in the <hi>Germans</hi> of old, and us now, to reſolve to defend our Countries from Popiſh Aggreſſors. I am ſure the <hi>Germans</hi> League was ſo neceſſary and ſo juſt, that a Popiſh French King aſſiſted them in it, and the Proteſtants were not all over-run by it, but are ſtill very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56682:31"/>and potent there. And when <hi>Denmark</hi> was in Danger, King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt thought it pious and lawfull to aſſiſt them; and <hi>Archbiſhop Laud</hi> drew up a Declaration to juſtifie and promote it, as our Author may ſee in the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s <hi>Papers,</hi> pag. 17. We grant it is no <hi>Chimera,</hi> that the Jeſuites have in all times ſolicited the Catholick Princes to unite for the Extirpation of <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſafe under a King conducted by their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. But the Proteſtants never did combine to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirminate Popery in general, and we do not fear that all Catholick Princes (moſt of them diſobliged by K. <hi>James</hi>) ſhould unite, to be reveng'd upon us, for not ſtopping our late King, when he reſolved to leave us: But withall, we obſerve how this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Writer blows both hot and cold, <hi>pag.</hi> 50th. He would fright us with the Pope's being in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy</hi> with King <hi>William,</hi> and with ſome ſolemn and ſacred <hi>Engagements</hi> made to the <hi>Holy Chair:</hi> And now he threatens us with an Army of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Princes, and the Pope in the Head of them, to deſtroy us, and all the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Europe.</hi> He may well call us Fools and Madmen (in the next Column:) For if he did not think us ſo, he would not hope to work on us, with ſuch incoherent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probabilities. He proceeds to deny, that the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>Europe</hi> are concern'd in the Iſſue of this War with <hi>France,</hi> becauſe divers <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> are in perfect Peace with that <hi>Crown.</hi> I reply firſt, they are all far diſtant from this Tyrant, and ſo do not yet feel the Effects of his <hi>Cruelty and Injuſtice;</hi> and ſecondly, they only ſtand Neuter, there being not one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince (now King <hi>James</hi> is gone off) who gives him actual Aſſiſtance; ſo that an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel Mahometan</hi> (to his eternal Reproach) is his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56682:32"/>only thorough-pac'd <hi>Confederate:</hi> Nor is it any great <hi>Glory</hi> to the <hi>French King,</hi> that all the States he could reach have been ſo wofully injured, and ſo barbarouſly treated by him, that he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated all his Neighbours againſt him; and the remoter Princes will repent, too late, of their <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality.</hi> If <hi>France</hi> ſhould enlarge its <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> all <hi>Europe,</hi> in time, may ſuffer, for not more early entring into this Confederacy: — <hi>Tua res agitur paries cum Proximus ardet.</hi>—
<q>
                  <l>To Day thy Neighbour's Houſe they burn,</l>
                  <l>To Morrow 'twill be thine own turn.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>His Adverſary doth not ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 56.</note> (as he falſely ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts,) That the Intereſt of our Prince and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, is, to give way to that of the other States: But when their Intereſts and ours agree, (as it doth, in hindering <hi>France</hi> from the Univerſal Monarchy it aims at,) it is a good Argument for our Prince and State, to confederate with other Nations in this Common Cauſe, without any Diſtinction on the Account of Religion: And being enter'd into ſo juſt a League, we are not to deſert our Allies, till their Dangers be averted, and their Injuries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, as well as ours. The laſt Caſe is not only probable, but certain: King <hi>James,</hi> his Temper, his Principles, his late Acts in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies who aſſiſt him, convince all thinking Men, that he will return with the ſame Deſigns he had before. But ſince, to divert this, he propoſes the giving up thoſe Miniſters of King <hi>William</hi> to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, who adviſed or aſſiſted in our Reſcue from Popery and Arbitrary Power; I will make another Propoſal, with humble Submiſſion to Authority:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56682:32"/>Which is this, That ſince King <hi>James</hi> his Prieſts and Popiſh Miniſters put him upon theſe illegal and miſchievous Methods, which haſtened his Fall, and hinder his Return; let him firſt give up all theſe Criminals to ſuffer what they deſerve by Law, and then we will treat with him concerning a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. I doubt he will not part with them for his Three Crowns; and if he will not come without them, and muſt have theſe implacable Enemies of our Religion and Liberties about him, he will be governed by them, and make uſe of them after his Reſtauration: And therefore we ſhall infallibly loſe our <hi>Troy,</hi> if we take in this Papal-Horſe, with his Belly-full of armed Foes; and the certain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of reſtoring him with this pernicious Crew about him, will be the perfecting thoſe Deſigns they ſo dangerouſly had begun; of which this Nation is ſo firmly perſwaded, that King <hi>James</hi> truly ſaid in <hi>Ireland,
<note n="*" place="margin">See Doctor <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>State of the Proteſtants in</hi> Ireland, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 49,</note> He never expected to get into</hi> England, <hi>but by Fire and Sword.</hi> Wherefore it was very juſt in one of our <hi>Author</hi>'s Adverſaries, to ſay, That <hi>the Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites Pangs of Loyalty were very unſeaſonable now.</hi> A little of this Loyalty before he went off, (if he durſt have truſted them, and they him,) had kept him on the <hi>Throne</hi> by a fair <hi>Treaty;</hi> which was all the Prince deſired: But then they let him ſink, ſeemed glad he was gone, and were as ready as any body to put the Government into the Prince's Hands, out of which (after the <hi>Nation</hi> hath fixed it there) they cannot tear it again, but they muſt involve their Native Countrey in a bloody Civil War, and expoſe us to <hi>French Incendiaries</hi> and Dragoons, who will ſoon waken them out of their ſenſeleſs <hi>Lethargy;</hi> and make thoſe who invited them in, wiſh, (with half their Eſtates) to hire them out again.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:56682:33"/>
The greateſt part of the Nation believe that King <hi>James</hi> his Deſertion vacated the Oath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taken to him;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 57.</note> therefore theſe, with a good Conſcience, took the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> to King <hi>William,</hi> and think themſelves obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him; theſe muſt and will fight for him: Some few, perhaps, mocked God, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King, in taking them, to ſave their <hi>Bacon:</hi> But no <hi>Caſuiſt</hi> need to trouble himſelf to ſolve ſuch Mens Caſes; for this Hypocriſie and Profaneneſs ſhews they have no Conſcience, and will neither be true to any Religion, or any Prince; but to be ſure, the loweſt ſence that any honeſt Man (who hath ſworn Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi>) could take that Oath in, is to live peaceably, and not to fight againſt, or betray him to whom they have ſolemnly vowed <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance:</hi> And if they do look upon their Oath as Conditional, however, it binds them till King <hi>William</hi> deſert us, as King <hi>James</hi> did; or, till he utterly break the Original Contract, (not by a few unavoidable <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi> as our <hi>Author</hi> grants, <hi>pag.</hi> 12. but) by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to overthrow the whole <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and Main Body of the Laws; and we need deſire their Faith and Allegiance no longer, than till one or both of theſe happen. But as for thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare they ought to fight againſt this <hi>Government,</hi> ſo ſoon as an Enemy appears; I hope the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> will withdraw its <hi>Protection</hi> from them, and pair their Nails in time. His Jeſt, of our expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Allegiance by <hi>Abdication,</hi> will not paſs; for we ſay, King <hi>James</hi> caſt off our Allegiance, when he left to Protect us: We did not Depoſe him, but he Deſerted us; and our Allegiance doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56682:33"/>bind us to keep him in his Throne, when he will not ſtay; nor to live in <hi>Anarchy</hi> till he return; no, nor to take him again on ill Terms; eſpecially when we have a far better Prince, whoſe Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Conduct and Intereſt is ſuch, that they who attempt to force him from us, muſt involve their Native Countrey in a bloody War: And to hinder them from ſo fatal a Purpoſe, we may properly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them to conſider of the ſad Examples of the Wars between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> between King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and of the Miſeries <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> ſuffered by Civil Wars: For they who impoſe an Abdicated King upon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing People, by Foreign Forces, are the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and muſt anſwer for all the Blood and Calamities that do enſue.</p>
            <p>Our Revolution was manag'd without Blood;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 57.</note> and if any attempt, by Force, to obtrude another, we cannot, by Perjury and Ingratitude, forſake that Prince whom we freely choſe, when we were left without a <hi>Governour,</hi> and who reſcued us from apparent Ruine. We have not hurt our <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and have happily ſetled both Church and State: We have no Diſeaſe now; and if we had, the <hi>French</hi> Phyſicians generally Let too much Blood, to be truſted with our Cure. And this <hi>State-Mountebank</hi> adviſes a Remedy ten times worſe than any Diſeaſe we can fall into, under this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for he would have us take up the Sword again, that wounded us; and give our ſelves a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wound, to cure the Firſt; which is irrational and abſurd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:56682:34"/>
The Payments its confeſſed are greater than they need have been, if K. <hi>J</hi>'s Friends did not encourage the <hi>French</hi> to invade us; but by theſe Payments <hi>England</hi> is delivered from <hi>Popery and Slavery,</hi> and remains in <hi>Peace,</hi> while the War is carried into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Country: And <hi>Ireland</hi> is reſcued out of the Claws of <hi>French-men, Tories and Rapparees:</hi> Our Government is ſettled in <hi>Church and State,</hi> and all his Endeavours to aggravate the Price of theſe ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable Bleſſings turns upon himſelf. For when we have paid (as he ſaith) as much as we are able to bring things to a Settlement, it cannot be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted we can or ought to pay more to unſettle us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: A tyred Horſe can endure no Addition to his Load. If we can ſpare but a little more to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our Defender, I hope we ſhall not find Money to pay the late King's Debts to the <hi>French,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by his own Wilfulneſs; nor ſhall we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pay Money, to hire Executioners to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>If the Payments will not draw the <hi>Nation</hi> to Mutiny,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 59.</note> he hopes the ill Succeſs of our Arms will; and to make this Falſhood paſs, he ſpits all his <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome</hi> at our brave King, on whom (as on the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and Delight of Mankind) either <hi>Victory,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Honour and Safety,</hi> always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends. It hath been obſerved indeed of K. <hi>J.</hi> that he ever brings ill <hi>Fortune</hi> to the ſide he takes, and never won a Battel in his Life: But for this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernary <hi>French Pen</hi> to turn this <hi>Character on King</hi> William, who hath ſo often delivered oppreſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conquered their Oppreſſours, or redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to Reaſon; is the height of Impudence:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56682:34"/>His <hi>Victories</hi> in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> will be writ in the Leaves of <hi>Fame,</hi> when the Great Monſieur will only be remembred for his Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and Treachery. K. <hi>William</hi>'s reducing a whole Kingdom laſt year, and beating the French Fleet this Summer, were great Actions; and his daring their whole Army by Land ſhews, that if (through others ſlackneſs) the French have the Advantage, yet he hath entirely the Honour of this Campaign, wherein K. <hi>Lewis</hi> hath had ſuch Experience of our King's Valour and Conduct, as will give him Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by an honourable Peace, to endeavour to make us his <hi>Friends:</hi> And if we get no more for all our Charge, but Security and Quiet, while the War endures, and a profitable Peace at the End of it, we need not murmur; or if we do, it ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Common Enemy, who diſturbs all that are within his Reach.</p>
            <p>He owns a Debt to the French King,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Page</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes his tender Regard to his Honour and Glory, will make him forgive it, and not require Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Dutch have done. But firſt as to the Monſieur, if he believe <hi>Honour</hi> to be the only <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Vertue,</hi> he hath taken the worſt Meaſures in the World to get true Glory; having not got one Inch of Ground, nor a ſingle Town by true <hi>Valour and Bravery,</hi> nor omitted any thing, tho' never ſo mean or wicked, which he thought ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſet up his only God, his <hi>Intereſt;</hi> and will Honour keep ſuch a Prince from demanding Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for his Men and Money, his Ships and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, lent to ſerve our late King? he that will burn a whole <hi>Country</hi> to Aſhes, and turn 500 Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies a begging in a day or two, only for not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56682:35"/>paying him <hi>Contributions</hi> when they owe him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor cannot raiſe it; will his <hi>Generoſity</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>England</hi> to dye in his Debt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secondly.</note> The <hi>Dutch</hi> deſire no more than that <hi>Hire</hi> was promiſed them for their Men and Ships, and they deſerve it, for helping us now in our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Danger, as we once before did aſſiſt them, when they beat out <hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Perſecution:</hi> Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this kind are tollerable, but to repay the <hi>French</hi> King for fighting againſt us, is ſo groſs a Folly, that Engliſh-men cannot be guilty of it. As to <hi>Religion,</hi> it is the <hi>Glory</hi> of our Nation, that we are ſo tender of it, ſo zealous, and ſo careful to preſerve it. The only Scandal to our Church, being this, that ſo many Pretenders to it, are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to joyn with <hi>Papiſts</hi> to deſtroy it: But theſe Gentlemen are but a ſmall Number; the greateſt part of the Nation are not ſo eaſily wheedled or threatned out of their <hi>Religion,</hi> their <hi>Liberties,</hi> their <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Lives;</hi> they know their Foes from their Friends, and underſtand when they are well; ſo that this plauſible Writer, with all his Rhetorick, will not be able to ſpread the Poyſon of his <hi>Sedition,</hi> ſo far as his Hopes flatters him.</p>
            <p>To conclude:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 61.</note> Finding his Arguments will not make K. <hi>William</hi> and his People fall out and part, to make room for his dear Maſter; he falls to Praying and Flattering, deſiring <hi>God</hi> to encline our King's Heart to take his Counſel, who mortally hates him, ſhamefully ſlanders him, and every where repreſents him as the worſt of Humane Race; and after this, with a ſmooth <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> even humbly deſires him freely to give up that <hi>Crown</hi> which he hath been
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56682:35"/>urging the <hi>Nation</hi> to take from him. But where ſuch Folly is cried up as <hi>Heroick,</hi> King <hi>William</hi>'s Eyes are open enough to ſee the dull and obvious Cheat: And One would imagine, he durſt not offer ſuch palpable <hi>Shams</hi> to ſo Great and Wiſe a <hi>Prince:</hi> But 'tis plain, he hath ſo accuſtomed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> that he can bluſh at nothing; and begins to dream, that our preſent King is ſuch a Creature, as he repreſents King <hi>James</hi> to be; One that was adviſed by his mortal Enemies to the ready way to ruine Himſelf, and all his Friends. But after all his elaborate <hi>Harangues,</hi> he muſt e'en be content to ſee King <hi>William</hi> deſpiſe his Railing and his Flattery, the <hi>Nation</hi> deteſt his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Counſel, and <hi>God</hi> caſt out his fooliſh Prayer, who hath moſt graciouſly preſerved our <hi>King</hi> and our <hi>Countrey</hi> hitherto; and till he do utterly aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don us, and deprive us of Grace, yea, of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sence, we cannot be ſo weak, as to promote this fatal <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> which he ſo vehemently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56682:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56682:36"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books lately Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>☞ THE State of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Government; in which their Carriage towards him is juſtified, and the abſolute Neceſſity of their endeavouring to be freed from his Government, and of ſubmitting to Their preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, is demonſtrated. The Fourth Edition, with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bede Venerabili Opera quaedam Theologica nunc primum edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta necnon Hiſtorica ante à ſemel edita acceſſerunt Egberti Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopi Eborocenſis Dialogus de Eccleſiaſtica Inſtitutione &amp; Aldhelmi Epiſcopi Scireburnenſis Liber de Virginitate ex codicae antiquiſſimo emendatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Defence of Pluralities, or holding Two Benifices with Cure of Souls, as now practiſed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. Annaei Flori Rerum Romanorum Epitome, interpretatione, &amp; Notis illuſtravit Anna Tanaquilli Fabri Filia, Juſſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſmi Regis, in uſum Sereniſſimi Delphini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Presbyteratu Diſſertatio Quadripartita, Presbyteratus Sacri Origines, Naturam Titulum, Officia &amp; Ordines, ab ipſis Mundi primordiis uſque ad Catholicae Eccleſiae conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Plantationem complectens. In qua Hierarchiae Epiſcpalis Jus divinum &amp; Immutabile, ex Auctoritate Scripturarum Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicè expoſitarum, &amp; Eccleſiaſticae traditionis Suffragiis, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter quidem, ſed luculentèr aſſeritur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martindal</hi>'s Art of Surveying.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56682:37"/>
The Frauds of the Romiſh Monks and Prieſts, ſet forth in Eight Letters, lately written by a Gentleman in his Journey into <hi>Italy.</hi> The Third Edition.</p>
            <p>Obſervations on a Journey to <hi>Naples;</hi> wherein the Frauds of Romiſh Monks and Prieſts are farther diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: By the Author of the former Book.</p>
            <p>Forms of Private Devotions for every Day in the Week, by a Method agreeable to the Liturgy: With Occaſional Prayers, and an Office for the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and for the time of Sickneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compendium Graecum Novi Teſtamenti, Continens, ex</hi> 7059. <hi>verſiculis totius. N. Teſtamenti, tantum verſiculos</hi> 1900. <hi>(non tamen integros) in quibus omnes univerſi Novi Teſt. voces, una cum verſione Latina, inveniuntar. Auctore</hi> Johanne Leuſden, <hi>Philoſ. Doctore, &amp; Linguae Sanctae in Academia ultrajectina Profeſſore ordinarie. Editio Quinta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Roman Forgeries in the Councils, during the Firſt Four Centuries: Together with an Appendix concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Forgeries and Errors in the Annals of <hi>Baronius.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Comber,</hi> D. D. Prebend of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56682:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
